<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Ad Hoc</title>
    <link href="https://gadgetboy.org/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://gadgetboy.org" />
    <updated>2020-12-07T08:43:38-06:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>John A. Federico</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://gadgetboy.org</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Creating in Public: A New Series</title>
        <author>
            <name>John A. Federico</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://gadgetboy.org/creating-in-public-a-new-series/"/>
        <id>https://gadgetboy.org/creating-in-public-a-new-series/</id>
            <category term="Podcasting"/>
            <category term="Linux"/>
            <category term="Gadgets"/>
            <category term="Creativity"/>
            <category term="Communication"/>
            <category term="Audio Production"/>

        <updated>2020-12-07T08:43:38-06:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/55/mic_ham.jpg" alt="" />
                    Welcome to a new series, Creating in Public. Creating in Public is&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/55/mic_ham.jpg" alt="" />
                <p>Welcome to a new series, <em>Creating in Public.</em> </p>
<p><em>Creating in Public</em> is my journey back to the joy of media creation. </p>
<p>You’re probably thinking, “Wait, isn’t media creation typically a public endeavour?” Well, yes, the final product is usually public, but in this series, I’m going to share everything <strong>as it happens</strong>.</p>
<h2 id="background">Background</h2>
<p>During high school, I was the “AV Geek.” It was a perk of being a member of the AV Club and it occasionally got me out of classes to do stuff that I enjoyed.</p>
<p>In college, I earned a double major: in addition to Marketing, I earned a BA in Media Production.</p>
<p>I had an on-campus job managing AV in the student center and theater and got to experience new technologies that I would otherwise never have access to - things like the LCD projectors that we all take for granted now and wireless audio gear.</p>
<p>And, yes, I was a DJ and radio personality on our college radio station. (Due to FCC regulations, the station was so low-powered that it only covered about 4 square miles. I used to joke on air, “<em>Welcome to WMAR! We’re a big cordless phone</em>!”) Then there was that time that students kept calling in to request <em>Rock Lobster</em> by the B52’s over and over again - so I played it for an hour. (The station manager was not pleased.)</p>
<p>So, in 2005, when podcasting became a thing, I jumped in with both feet, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20061205232849/http://www.odmcast.com/podcast/">producing a show</a> that had tens of thousands of downloads per month - small numbers by today’s standards, but we were very proud of the worldwide community we built. After a number of life changes by me and my co-hosts - new jobs, cross-country relocation - we finally ended the show. While we all enjoyed producing it, getting everyone to connect at the same time for recording was like herding cats.</p>
<p>In 2012 I started <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC4JNMvDlG4ODohb-Nfz0rqg/videos">another podcast</a> focused on the niche of event technology for a company that I co-founded. I wanted to meet as many industry trend makers as possible and an interview show was a great way to do that. It was particularly great at conferences where the organizers would provide us with some space to record interviews and capture video. After a couple of years, the organizers used to tout it as a benefit to attendees and sponsors. That came to an end when I left the company in late 2017.</p>
<p>Since then, I’ve been heads down working at a ginormous tech company creating new software partnerships and building new products.</p>
<p>As busy as I’ve been, I really missed the fun of producing media and a few months ago, decided to dive back into the pool.</p>
<p>This series will cover the steps I have been (and will be) taking including:</p>
<ul>
<li>Creating a show concept based on a topic that I love, that works with my schedule and minimizes post-production</li>
<li>Naming the show</li>
<li>Setting up a new home studio including new audio gear and acoustic treatment</li>
<li>Creating new workflows for the Linux desktop, including DAW’s, Windows Virtual Machines and other nerdy stuff</li>
<li>Utilizing podcast technologies <em>that didn’t exist</em> even a few years ago</li>
<li>Giving up some control to SaaS platforms, instead of self-hosting all my backend and frontend technology</li>
<li>Securing interviews with industry leaders when I currently have zero listeners, using only my reputation and network of friends and colleagues to make connections</li>
<li>Finding  and using royalty-free music and sound effects</li>
<li>Adding video (when appropriate)</li>
<li>Marketing and promoting the show</li>
<li>Other Shenanigans</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="join-me">Join Me</h2>
<p>If you want to join me on this journey, sign-up for email updates (below) or go ahead and <a href="https://gadgetboy.org/feed">subscribe to this blog in your favorite RSS reader</a>.</p>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>From Full-Stack Podcaster to PINO</title>
        <author>
            <name>John A. Federico</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://gadgetboy.org/from-full-stack-podcaster-to-pino/"/>
        <id>https://gadgetboy.org/from-full-stack-podcaster-to-pino/</id>
            <category term="Podcasting"/>
            <category term="Audio Production"/>

        <updated>2020-11-02T18:57:21-06:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/54/Blue_Encore_200.jpg" alt="Blue Encore 200" />
                    I started writing this in the comment section of an episode of&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/54/Blue_Encore_200.jpg" alt="Blue Encore 200" />
                <p>I started writing this in the comment section of <a href="https://podcastpontifications.com/episode/why-pinos-podcasters-in-name-only-own-the-future">an episode of Podcast Pontifications</a> (“Why PINOs - Podcasters In Name Only - Own The Future”) and for some reason I decided to turn it into a blog post. You can subscribe to Podcast Pontifications in <a href="https://podcastpontifications.substack.com/">newsletter</a> or <a href="https://www.podchaser.com/podcasts/podcast-pontifications-740003">podcast</a> format. It’s also available on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCldrmtlLrlNA8G2vz_Rs_OQ">YouTube</a>, if that’s your thing.</p>
<h2 id="original-gangster">Original Gangster</h2>
<p>OG Podcaster here, and I’m working on a concept for a new show.</p>
<p>And, guess what?</p>
<p>I’m <strong>only</strong> returning to podcasting because I no longer have to be what <a href="https://twitter.com/evoterra">Evo Terra</a> refers to as a “full-stack podcaster”. </p>
<p>A full-stack podcaster is someone who, back in the day, <strong>had</strong> to be well-versed in audio recording, editing and mixdown along with things like generating a properly formatted RSS feed so that your podcast could make its way into whatever podcast app your audience chooses.</p>
<p>I’ve produced and hosted two of my own shows since 2005. The first was a panel-style show that required herding the proverbial cats into my home studio every Thursday night (Remember, this was 2005 and things like Skype recording were still a PITA), edit the show, post it and do my best to promote it. I had so many issues with certain Wordpress plugins that I ultimately started creating my feeds by hand, using <a href="https://reinventedsoftware.com/feeder/">Feeder</a>, then hosting it on Amazon S3 and their Cloudfront CDN.</p>
<p>The second show was a little easier, since it was an interview-style format and I produced it in support of my company. I could do it during “normal” working hours, but it was still a full-stack production.</p>
<p>It was the first show, the <em>extracurricular activity</em>, that pushed me toward my current mindset and the key thought is this: I will <strong>not</strong> produce another show unless I can have the simplest workflow possible.</p>
<p>That’s it. That’s the most important part.</p>
<p>The concept of the show is designed both around the content and creativity that make it work <strong>and</strong> the workflow. I had other creative concepts for the show but realized they would take up too much time and effort, and my day job already demands too much of my time. I want my next show to be a creative outlet and not something that feels like a second job.</p>
<p>If nothing else, it has made me rethink my workflows and equipment.</p>
<p>Let’s start there: equipment. </p>
<h2 id="gear">Gear</h2>
<p>I am selling <strong>all</strong> of my outboard gear (vocal strips, noise gate, mixers, USB audio interface, portable recorders, etc.) and buying an <strong>all-in-one setup</strong> with onboard signal processing, simple mix-minus, etc. </p>
<p>Right now, the <a href="https://amzn.to/37UNHzH">Rodecaster Pro</a> is at the top of my list but I’m waiting for reviews of the <a href="https://www.bhphotovideo.com/c/product/1592739-REG/zoom_zp8_podtrak_p8_portable_multitrack.html">Podtrak P8</a> from working podcasters and not just B&amp;H or Sweetwater, who both sell the device. (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xVUXqUKHx1o">I like A.B.</a>, and think that he does thorough reviews, but I want a diversity of opinions.)</p>
<p>I’ll keep my beloved <a href="https://amzn.to/3oMSn0i">Sony MDR-7506</a> headphones, <a href="https://amzn.to/3kMDloW">MXL 990</a>, Blue Encore 100 and <a href="http://recordinghacks.com/microphones/Kel-Audio/HM1">Kel Audio HM-1</a>, but everything else will be posted on eBay or Craigslist.</p>
<p>When dry, the <a href="https://amzn.to/3oS2Dor">Blue Encore 100</a> sounds very similar to the Shure <a href="https://amzn.to/3ebaacW">SM58</a> (which itself sounds very similar to the Shure <a href="https://amzn.to/35QRYS3">SM7B</a>) so that will likely be my go-to mic.</p>
<h2 id="editing-and-post-production">Editing and Post-Production</h2>
<p>I am <strong>completely</strong> sold on <a href="https://www.descript.com/">Descript</a> and its ability to quickly transcribe and edit the audio using text. (And have you seen the Overdub feature?! Could there be anything more “PINO” than that?) The product is amazing and appears to be well worth the $24/month for the Pro plan. (Though paying for a year upfront is a little painful.)</p>
<p>If I decide that I want to get into more detailed editing, Descript will export the timeline to <a href="https://www.reaper.fm/">Reaper</a>, my preferred DAW on Linux.</p>
<h2 id="hosting">Hosting</h2>
<p>Most recently, I self-hosted a Wordpress instance for the web site and a discrete Wordpress instance for the RSS feed. I uploaded the audio files to Soundcloud or Amazon S3.</p>
<p>This time around, I’m going the SaaS route to help cut down my total production time. </p>
<p>At the top of my list right now is <a href="https://www.captivate.fm/">Captivate</a>. It looks like the best mix of features and price and if the show becomes popular, it can grow with me.</p>
<h2 id="monetization">Monetization</h2>
<p>This isn’t even on my mind, right now. You can’t monetize without an audience, so I’m totally focused on creativity and growing a base of listeners. If the show becomes popular, I’ll worry about it then - <strong>but</strong> if I reach that point, I’m still going to let <strong>someone else</strong> sell the ad positions. I don’t have time for that.</p>
<h2 id="does-all-of-this-make-me-a-pino">Does all of this make me a PINO?</h2>
<p>If you like what you hear, who cares?</p>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Cleaning House</title>
        <author>
            <name>John A. Federico</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://gadgetboy.org/cleaning-house/"/>
        <id>https://gadgetboy.org/cleaning-house/</id>
            <category term="Software"/>

        <updated>2020-09-27T12:10:29-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/52/delete_key2_1600.jpg" alt="Delete Key" />
                    In my perpetual quest to learn something new and interesting, I gave&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/52/delete_key2_1600.jpg" alt="Delete Key" />
                <p>In my perpetual quest to learn something new and interesting, I gave this blog a complete overhaul.</p>
<p>For years, I self-hosted it on Wordpress. That was a pain, primarily because (at the time) it was difficult to lock down Wordpress and protect it from getting hacked. Couple that with things like mySQL and PHP updates and stuff was breaking all the time. I spent more time administering it than actually writing.</p>
<p>I moved it to Squarespace where it ran for a long time without issues until December 2018 when I made a DNS change (at the request of Squarespace) and it made the site unreachable. Squarespace support was of no help in fixing the issue, so I decided to move it to a basic Wordpress.com site using their Squarespace import tool.</p>
<p>Wordpress.com is great. A fully-managed Personal blog is $4/month and, if you don’t want to use the traditional Wordpress interface, the new management interface is attractive and easy to use.</p>
<p>Where it started to get annoying was when I wanted to do simple things like customize my CSS or add a Google Analytics tracking tag and found that a Personal plan doesn’t allow for that - you have to upgrade to a Premium plan.</p>
<p>I get it - it’s SaaS and they have to price it properly to incentivize people to move up to plans with higher ARPU. But I also know that some of these things are trivial to enable and it felt unnecessarily restrictive.</p>
<p>So, during my <a href="https://gadgetboy.org/what-i-did-on-my-holiday-staycation-2020-edition/">Holiday Staycation</a>, I began to explore <a href="https://www.netlify.com/blog/2020/04/14/what-is-a-static-site-generator-and-3-ways-to-find-the-best-one/">static site generators</a>. Static sites are incredibly fast because there’s no server side processing of web pages - the web server simply delivers a pre-built file. More importantly, there’s no CMS running code so the attack vectors are (generally speaking) only the OS and the web server and not some insecure Wordpress plugin.</p>
<p>I was reading a lot of Home Assistant docs (another Staycation project) and noticed that they were using <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</a>, so I decided to give it a try. I like the simplicity of page generation using plain text files, markdown and YAML and I found a highly regarded python script to import Wordpress posts so I could migrate my current content to static files.</p>
<p>After some configuration, the import script worked great, but I was unable to figure out why I couldn’t get any theme other than the default to work. I finally ran out of tinker time and had to go back to the office.</p>
<p>A few weeks later, while my wife was attending a Yoga immersive for the weekend, I started exploring other options. As it turns out, there <a href="https://staticsitegenerators.net/">are <strong>a lot</strong> of static site generators out there</a>.</p>
<p>Ultimately, I chose <a href="https://getpublii.com/">Publii</a>. It’s an open source static site generator with a full GUI and lots of great features. There’s a built-in utility for Wordpress imports but then, as I was starting the process, I decided to take inventory of the content.</p>
<p>Much of it is outdated (Review of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treo_755p">Palm Treo 755p</a>, anyone?) or the equivalent of what would be social media posts today.</p>
<p>Sure, reviewing old posts was an interesting trip down Memory Lane but in the end, I decided to simply select posts to migrate manually, updating the URL structure and media file references accordingly.</p>
<p>My intention is to host this on a spare Raspberry Pi on my home network, just so I can learn how to set up things like dynamic DNS, domain-based routing through the firewall and reverse proxy configuration but for now, it’s hosted on GitHub Pages.</p>
<p>Publii is open source. If you want to support the project, you can contribute code or <a href="https://getpublii.com/donate/">make a donation</a>. I make a monthly donation through <a href="https://opencollective.com/publii/">Open Collective</a> but you can also make a donation via PayPal.</p>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Set Up Duplicacy on Pop!_OS 20.04</title>
        <author>
            <name>John A. Federico</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://gadgetboy.org/set-up-duplicacy-on-pop_os-2004/"/>
        <id>https://gadgetboy.org/set-up-duplicacy-on-pop_os-2004/</id>
            <category term="Tutorial"/>
            <category term="Pop!_OS"/>
            <category term="Linux"/>
            <category term="How-to"/>

        <updated>2020-05-10T09:54:59-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/duplicacy_backup_feature.png" alt="Set Up Duplicacy on Pop!_OS 20.04" />
                    I had no backup plan.I switched to Pop!_OS as my daily driver but&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/duplicacy_backup_feature.png" alt="Set Up Duplicacy on Pop!_OS 20.04" />
                <h2>I had no backup plan.</h2>
<p><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/review-system76-lemur-pro/" title="Review: System76 Lemur Pro" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">I switched to Pop!_OS as my daily driver </a>but I didn't yet move my files from my old MacBook Pro. Everything was backed up using Mac software, and I didn't have a plan for Linux backup.</p>
<p>On the Mac, I backed up locally to a 1 TB external USB 3.0 drive using Time Machine and off-site to Dropbox <em>and</em> Amazon S3 using Arq Backup. Yeah, it was overkill, but you can't put a price on data loss, especially 25 years of family photos and videos.</p>
<p>I also recently built a NAS system on my LAN for our family file storage, but it's not yet ready for backups, so I needed both a short term solution for my Linux laptop and a long term solution that I could use for all of our household backups.</p>
<p>It doesn't matter what your preferred backup software is but, in general, I follow these basic guidelines:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Automate</strong> your backups on a regular schedule</li>
<li>Have a <strong>local copy</strong> of your backups for quick retrieval (USB drive, NAS, etc.)</li>
<li>Have an <strong>off-site/cloud copy</strong> of your backups for redundancy</li>
<li>Check the <strong>integrity</strong> of your backups regularly</li>
<li>Have a recovery <strong>plan</strong>. (Do you know how to recover your data, especially since your backup software was running on your now dead computer?)</li>
</ul>
<p>After investigating a number of backup solutions, including <a href="https://github.com/teejee2008/timeshift" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="TimeShift on GitHub">TimeShift</a> and <a href="https://www.duplicati.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Duplicati Home">Duplicati</a>, I decided upon <a href="https://duplicacy.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Duplicacy Backup Software">Duplicacy</a>, mostly based upon community reviews.</p>
<p class="msg msg--info">Duplicacy is developed by <a href="https://acrosync.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Acrosync Home">Acrosync</a>. If you're comfortable working with the command line, there is <strong>no cost for a CLI license</strong> since it's open source. <em>Thanks, Acrosync.</em></p>
<p>While the core Duplicacy backup engine is open source, the web-GUI version is not, nor is it free. That's fine with me - I'm happy to contribute to open source projects through commercial offerings.</p>
<p>The pricing for a personal license is a little outside the norm - not quite SaaS, not quite a one-time purchase - but I ended up getting a 5-year license for $40.</p>
<p class="msg msg--info">The Duplicacy web-GUI version has a lengthy free trial period, so you have plenty of time to decide if it works for you.</p>
<p>Here's how to set it up.</p>
<h2>Wizards and Magic</h2>
<p>My experience with backup software has typically been wizard-driven:</p>
<p>[Launch backup software]</p>
<ol>
<li>What files would you like to backup?</li>
<li>Where do you want to put those files?</li>
<li>Do you want those files to be encrypted?</li>
<li>How often do you want to backup?</li>
<li>How long do you want to keep your backups?</li>
</ol>
<p>[Save]</p>
<p>After that, everything just backs up automagically.</p>
<p>Duplicacy addresses all the same considerations, but instead of being wizard-driven, set up is performed using commands and configuration files. Luckily, I could ramp up quickly using the web-GUI version. I'll use this version for my laptop, but will use the command line version for backing up my NAS to the cloud.</p>
<h2>Concepts</h2>
<p>To get started with Duplicacy, you first need to understand some concepts and definitions. Again, wizard-driven backup solutions use these same concepts, but they're abstracted. In Duplicacy, they are explicit and uniquely configured. This approach took me a few minutes to get my head around, but now it makes perfect sense.</p>
<h3>Repository</h3>
<p>A Repository is the location of the files that you want to backup. (e.g. /home/yourdirectory or /etc/opt)</p>
<h3>Snapshot ID</h3>
<p>A Snapshot ID is a unique identifier for the repository you want to backup. For example, if you want to backup your home directory, you might give it a Snapshot ID of "Home."</p>
<h3>Revision</h3>
<p>After the first backup of a repository, each subsequent backup generates a Revision. A revision contains the changes (additions, deletions, edits) since the last backup (sometimes referred to as Incremental or Differential backup). Revisions provide faster backups and conserve disk space.</p>
<h3>Storage</h3>
<p>Where will you store your backups? You will need to initialize that storage by providing a path to the local or remote file system. If you're backing up off-site to cloud storage, you'll need to authenticate with that service before you can select it as a backup location. The process of authenticating Duplicacy varies based on the service you're using, so I won't cover that here.</p>
<p>Currently, Duplicacy supports the following backends:</p>
<ul>
<li>Local File System</li>
<li>SFTP</li>
<li>Dropbox</li>
<li>Amazon S3 (or API equivalent)</li>
<li>Wasabi</li>
<li>DigitalOcean Spaces</li>
<li>Google Cloud</li>
<li>Microsoft Azure</li>
<li>Backblaze B2</li>
<li>Google Drive</li>
<li>Microsoft OneDrive</li>
<li>Hubic</li>
<li>OpenStack Swift</li>
<li>WebDav</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://forum.duplicacy.com/t/supported-storage-backends/1107" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Storage Backends on the Duplicacy Forum">You can find details and CLI commands on the Duplicacy Forum.</a></p>
<p>In my short term use case, I'll be backing up to a <a href="https://amzn.to/2zr7uaz" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Sandick High Endurance Micro SD Card 256 GB">High Endurance Micro SD card</a> (Local File System) every few hours and Google Drive each night.</p>
<p>When my NAS is properly set up, I plan to continue with the Micro SD card for hourly backups, use the NAS for nightly backups and use <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/glacier/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Amazon S3 Glacier &amp; S3 Glacier Deep Archive">Amazon S3 Glacier</a> for weekly off-site backups.</p>
<h3>Backup</h3>
<p>A Backup is defined as the collection of files or directories you want to backup and the location where you want to put them. In order to configure a Backup, you first need to have initialized your Storage.</p>
<h3>Schedule</h3>
<p>A Schedule contains the timing of your backups (Day, time of day, etc.) and the Backup job you want to run. You can have multiple schedules for the same backup, multiple backups in a single schedule, etc. In order to configure a Schedule, you first need to have initialized your Storage and created at least one Backup.</p>
<h3>Prune</h3>
<p>The Prune function is similar to step 5 in the wizard-driven software example above but again, you need to explicitly define it. To do this, you need to create a Schedule that runs a Prune job, select the appropriate Backup, then indicate the parameters for when to start pruning data.</p>
<h3>Restore</h3>
<p>You can restore your data from any shapshot contained in your backup library. Keep in mind that these are not bootable system backups - only your data. If your Linux installation doesn't have a bootable recovery partition, you may want to keep a bootable USB drive handy in case of system failure.</p>
<h3>Additional Concepts</h3>
<p>There are some additional concepts and commands that you may want to explore, but the above is enough to get you started.</p>
<h2>Setting up Duplicacy</h2>
<h3>Installation</h3>
<p>You have two options for installing the Duplicacy web version:</p>
<ol>
<li>Download a self-contained binary or;</li>
<li>Build it from source.</li>
</ol>
<p>I selected the easiest option and <a href="https://duplicacy.com/download.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Download Duplicacy">downloaded the binary for x64 systems</a>. Once downloaded, I ran a checksum to ensure that it wasn't corrupted.</p>
<p><code>cd /home/gadgetboy/Downloads</code></p>
<p><code>sha256sum duplicacy_web_linux_x64_1.3.0</code></p>
<p> Next, I moved the application to /opt/Duplicacy</p>
<p><code>sudo mkdir /opt/Duplicacy</code></p>
<p><code>sudo mv /home/gadgetboy/Downloads/duplicacy_web_linux_x64_1.3.0 /opt/Duplicacy</code></p>
<p>You also need to change permissions on the file so that it can be executed as a program. You can do this from the command line or using the Files application by right-clicking the file, selecting <strong>Permissions</strong>, then selecting the checkbox, "Allow executing file as program."</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/duplicacy_permissions_markup.png" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" srcset="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/responsive/duplicacy_permissions_markup-xs.png 300w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/responsive/duplicacy_permissions_markup-sm.png 480w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/responsive/duplicacy_permissions_markup-md.png 768w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/responsive/duplicacy_permissions_markup-lg.png 1024w"  alt="Set File as Executable in Files" width="461" height="493">
<figcaption >Set executable file permissions (Image Credit: me)</figcaption>
</figure>
<h4>Launching Duplicacy at Startup</h4>
<p>Even though Duplicacy is now ready to launch, you'll want to do one more thing: make sure Duplicacy launches after a restart. Otherwise, your automated backups won't run unless you remember to launch Duplicacy every time you reboot your machine.</p>
<p>Select the <strong>Activities</strong> menu in the Pop!_OS panel, in the top left corner. Select the <strong>Show Applications</strong> icon in the Dash, then find the <strong>Startup Applications</strong> app and launch it.</p>
<p>Click <strong>Add</strong>, then enter the name of the application. Next, enter the path of the application or select it by navigating to it by clicking <strong>Browse...</strong> </p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-columns="1">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/gallery/add_startup_program.png" data-size="663x599"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/gallery/add_startup_program-thumbnail.png" alt="Add Startup Program" width="663" height="599"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">Add Startup Program (Image Credit: me)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p class="msg msg--info"><strong>Optional:</strong> If you're not the only user or administrator of this machine, you may want to enter a comment so that other people know why it's set to run at startup.</p>
<p>Okay, we're finally ready to start backing up some files, so let's launch Duplicacy. It will load the control interface in your default web browser.</p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight  msg--info">The Duplicacy web-GUI version runs a small web server so that you can setup and manage it using a web browser. By default, it responds only to requests from <em>localhost</em> at 127.0.0.1:3875. If you'd like to change this configuration so you can access it remotely, you can do that by selecting <strong>Setting</strong> in the toolbar. I'm going to focus only on the localhost use case in this post. Review <a href="https://forum.duplicacy.com/t/how-to-access-the-duplicacy-web-interface-remotely/1664/7?u=christoph" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="How to access the duplicacy web-interface remotely">this forum post</a> if you'd like learn how to setup remote access.</p>
<h3>Application Password</h3>
<p>Duplicacy will ask you to create a password to secure your credentials stored in local configuration files. You can choose to store this password in your Keychain. I use <a href="https://bitwarden.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Bitwarden Home">Bitwarden</a> for all my passwords, so I unchecked this box.</p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight ">You can click any of the images below to enlarge them.</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-columns="1">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/gallery/duplicacy_web_password.png" data-size="1247x567"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/gallery/duplicacy_web_password-thumbnail.png" alt="Duplicacy Web Password Entry" width="768" height="349"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">Duplicacy Web Password Entry (Image Credit: Acrosync)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p>Once your password has been configured, Duplicacy will load the Dashboard. There's nothing yet to see here since we haven't yet initializied Storage, created a Backup or set a Schedule.</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-columns="1">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/gallery/duplicacy_web_start.png" data-size="1247x567"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/gallery/duplicacy_web_start-thumbnail.png" alt="Duplicacy Web Start Up" width="768" height="349"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">Duplicacy Web Start Up (Image Credit: Acrosync)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<h3>Identifying and Initializing Storage</h3>
<p>To add a place to store your backups, select <strong>Storage</strong> from the toolbar, then select the "<strong>+</strong>" icon in the lower left corner of the screen. You'll be presented with the Storage configuration options.</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-columns="1">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/gallery/duplicacy_storage_configuration.png" data-size="611x298"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/gallery/duplicacy_storage_configuration-thumbnail.png" alt="Duplicacy Storage Selection" width="611" height="298"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">Duplicacy Storage Selection (Image Credit: me)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p>I'm going to continue on with own use case in this how-to, so I'll select a directory on my Micro SD card.</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-columns="1">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/gallery/select_storage_location.png" data-size="614x546"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/gallery/select_storage_location-thumbnail.png" alt="Select Storage Location for Backups" width="614" height="546"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">Select Storage Location for Backups (Image Credit: me)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p>Finally, to initialize the Storage, you'll need to give it a name. You can optionally add a password used to encrypt your Storage (<strong>RECOMMENDED</strong>).</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-columns="1">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/gallery/storage_name_password.png" data-size="608x545"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/gallery/storage_name_password-thumbnail.png" alt="Naming your Storage" width="608" height="545"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">Naming your Storage (Image Credit: me)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p class="msg msg--info"><strong>Optional:</strong> Select the Copy-compatible checkbox to explicitly indicate that the source Storage is compatible with the destination storage.</p>
<p>Execute this operation by clicking the <strong>Add</strong> button. Once completed, the Storage will appear when you select <strong>Storage</strong> from the toolbar. In the screenshot below, you'll see the storage for both my hourly backups to the Micro SD card ("2004_Backups") and my Nightly backups to Google Drive ("Nightly").</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-columns="1">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/gallery/initialized_storage.png" data-size="1276x853"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/gallery/initialized_storage-thumbnail.png" alt="Initialized Storage" width="768" height="513"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">Initialized Storage (Image Credit: me)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<h3>Defining a Backup</h3>
<p>Select <strong>Backup</strong> from the toolbar, then click the "<strong>+</strong>" button in the upper right corner. Here, you'll select the <strong>Directory</strong> (your files) that you want to backup, the destination (the initialized Storage created above) and a <strong>Backup ID</strong>. Give your Backup ID a memorable name like "My_Home_Directory" or "My_Photos."</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-columns="1">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/gallery/define_duplicacy_backup.png" data-size="611x542"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/gallery/define_duplicacy_backup-thumbnail.png" alt="Define a Backup in Duplicacy" width="611" height="542"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">Define a Backup in Duplicacy (Image Credit: me)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p>Save this configuration by clicking the <strong>Save</strong> button. You'll return to the Backup screen where you will now see your new Backup configuration. In the screenshot below, you'll see both my local Backup ("home") and my Google Drive Backup ("Offsite").</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-columns="1">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/gallery/duplicacy_configured_backup.png" data-size="1277x849"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/gallery/duplicacy_configured_backup-thumbnail.png" alt="Duplicacy Backup Configured" width="768" height="511"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">Duplicacy Backup Configured (Image Credit: me)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p>In theory, you could stop here. When you want to perform a backup, you could just click the green arrow/triangle below the Backup name, but we don't want to have to remember to do that - we want it to happen automatically.</p>
<h3>Creating a Schedule</h3>
<p>Select <strong>Schedule</strong> from the toolbar, then select the "<strong>+</strong>" icon in the lower left corner. Give your Schedule a name (e.g. "Nightly"), select the <strong>time of day</strong> you'd like it to start, select the <strong>frequency</strong> in which you want it to run, then select the <strong>day(s) of the week</strong> you would like it to run.</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-columns="1">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/gallery/duplicacy_create_schedule.png" data-size="611x544"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/gallery/duplicacy_create_schedule-thumbnail.png" alt="Creat a Schedule in Duplicacy" width="611" height="544"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">Creat a Schedule in Duplicacy (Image Credit: me)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p class="msg msg--highlight  msg--info"><strong>Optional:</strong> Select the <strong>Maximum Run Time</strong>. I don't particularly grok the use case for this. Perhaps if it's a production machine, like a file server, you'd want to make sure it's finished before 9 AM, when people start working. Or, maybe, if it's your laptop and you need to leave for work at a certain time, you want to make sure you don't interrupt the job and corrupt the backup. Someone with more experience will have to give me a real use case. Personally, I want the job to finish, no matter how long it takes.</p>
<h3>Testing</h3>
<p>This is the last and most important step in any backup plan. If you don't validate your backup, it's like not having a backup at all.</p>
<p>Click <strong>Backup</strong> from the toolbar.</p>
<p>Run a manual Backup job by clicking the green arrow icon. If this is your first time, go get a cup of coffee. Or a cocktail. It could take a while.</p>
<p>Once the job is completed, click <strong>Restore</strong> from the toolbar.</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-columns="1">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/gallery/duplicacy_restore.png" data-size="1266x848"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/gallery/duplicacy_restore-thumbnail.png" alt="Duplicacy Restore Screen" width="768" height="514"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">Duplicacy Restore Screen (Image Credit: me)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p>Select the initialized <strong>Storage</strong> where your backups are kept from the drop down menu, then select the <strong>Backup ID</strong> of your files. Now, select a <strong>Revision</strong>. This could be from any point in time as indicated by the time stamp at the end of each entry. Finally, indicate the directory where you'd like to put your restored files.</p>
<p class="msg msg--info">For information on <strong>Options</strong>, visit the <a href="https://forum.duplicacy.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Duplicacy forum">Duplicacy forum</a>.</p>
<p>After you've selected your revision, Duplicacy will present you with the files or directories contained within. Select the file or directory that you want to restore, then click the <strong>Restore</strong> button at the bottom of the screen. </p>
<p>Your files will be unpacked and copied to the directory you've specified above.</p>
<h3>Review Your Files</h3>
<p>Does everything look OK? Is anything missing? Are you able to open your files? Yes?</p>
<p class="msg msg--success"><strong>Congratulations!</strong> You've set up the Duplicacy web-GUI version to backup your files automatically.</p>
<h3>The Check Job</h3>
<p>You've now setup Duplicacy and performed a successful backup and restore of your data, but do you plan to do that after <em>every</em> backup?</p>
<p>Of course not.</p>
<p>To ensure Snapshot integrity, you'll want to run the <strong>Check</strong> command. You can run a Check at any time but it's probably best to schedule a Check job after a completed backup.</p>
<p>By default, the Check command will only verify that a referenced file chunk exists in your snapshots. If you want to automatically verify the integrity of each individual file, see <a href="https://forum.duplicacy.com/t/check-command-details/1081" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Check command details">this post on the Duplicacy forum</a> for options.</p>
<p>To setup a Check job, you can create a new schedule or add the job to an existing schedule. In my case, I've added it to my "Nightly" schedule so that it runs after each daily cloud backup.</p>
<p>Once your schedule is created, click the "<strong>+</strong>" icon to add a new job. Select <strong>Check</strong> from the drop down menu, then select which <strong>Destination</strong> you want to check. To learn more about <strong>Options</strong>, visit the forum post linked above.</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-columns="1">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/gallery/duplicacy_add_new_check_job.png" data-size="612x391"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/gallery/duplicacy_add_new_check_job-thumbnail.png" alt="Add a new Check job in Duplicacy" width="612" height="391"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">Add a new Check job in Duplicacy (Image Credit: me)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<h3>Pruning</h3>
<p>Technically, you're all set: your backups now run on an automated schedule and you can safely restore your data.</p>
<p>But unless you have unlimited storage, you'll probably only want to keep backups around for a certain length of time.</p>
<p>To configure this, we have to create a <strong>Prune</strong> job.</p>
<p>To recap, I backup my home directory to the Micro SD card every 4 hours. Then, each night, I backup my home directory to Google Drive. (That's two Storage locations, two Backup jobs and two Schedules, if you're keeping track.)</p>
<p>I created two daily Prune jobs for each referenced Backup.</p>
<p>To create a Prune job, select <strong>Schedule</strong> from the toolbar, then select the "<strong>+</strong>" icon in the bottom left of the main screen to create a new schedule. In my case, I prune both my local backups and my cloud backups every 7 days. Choose what works for your peace of mind and your storage limitations.</p>
<p>Give your schedule a logical name such as "Prune_Local" or "Prune_Cloud." If you intend to run multiple jobs in the same schedule, name the schedule accordingly.</p>
<p>Now, find your new schedule in the main screen and select the "<strong>+</strong>" icon to add a job to it. This is just like adding the Backup job that we covered above, but instead of selecting <strong>Backup</strong> from the drop down menu, we're going to select <strong>Prune</strong>.</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-columns="1">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/gallery/duplicacy_prune_setup.png" data-size="613x532"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/46/gallery/duplicacy_prune_setup-thumbnail.png" alt="Duplicacy Prune Job Setup" width="613" height="532"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">Duplicacy Prune Job Setup (Image Credit: me)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p>Next, select the <strong>Destination</strong> (your initialized Storage) that you want to Prune and configure your <strong>Retention Policy</strong>. Click <strong>Save</strong> to finish.</p>
<p> </p>
If you found this how-to helpful, pay it forward.
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Protect your Privacy with Firefox Containers</title>
        <author>
            <name>John A. Federico</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://gadgetboy.org/protect-your-privacy-with-firefox-containers/"/>
        <id>https://gadgetboy.org/protect-your-privacy-with-firefox-containers/</id>

        <updated>2020-07-06T07:07:55-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/45/shipping_containers_firefox.png" alt="Shipping Containers" />
                    Absolute privacy is dead. There's just too much personal information and metadata&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/45/shipping_containers_firefox.png" alt="Shipping Containers" />
                <p>Absolute privacy is dead. </p>
<p>There's just too much personal information and metadata about you collected from too many sources and you have no control over any of it - who has it, how it's used, how it can be combined - nothing. Privacy regulations like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/General_Data_Protection_Regulation" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="GDPR on Wikipedia">GDPR</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California_Consumer_Privacy_Act" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="CCPA on Wikipedia">CCPA</a> are a step in the right direction, but they won't protect you nearly as much as they claim.</p>
<p>In the "good old days," (prior to 1995) marketers and other users of personal information were basically limited to credit card data (sold by your credit card company, natch), public records (e.g. the car you own, your address) and consumer research.</p>
<p>Today, there is a treasure trove of data available about you, your habits and your intentions based solely on your online activity. </p>
<p>Going forward, the best you can hope for is to prevent further escape of your personal information and metadata into the wild. (Sometimes referred to as "<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_exhaust" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Data Exhaust on Wikipedia">data exhaust</a>.")</p>
<p>But how?</p>
<h2>The use (and abuse) of Cookies</h2>
<p>There are many types of strategies and tactics for capturing your personal metadata, but the greatest culprit is probably browser cookies.</p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HTTP_cookie" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="HTTP Cookie on Wikipedia">Cookies</a> were originally created by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netscape" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Netscape on Wikipedia">Netscape</a> in the 1990's for use in their Navigator web browser. Their original design was to uniquely identify internet users to help ecommerce sites keep track of what items are in your shoppping cart.</p>
<p>Since then, they've been used for a variety of reasons, almost all of which are designed to <strong>track you on the internet</strong>.</p>
<p>Cross-site tracking cookies are the worst offenders.</p>
<p>These cookies are delivered by companies like ad networks, analytics and research providers, social media sites and ecommerce sites, among others.</p>
<p>Have you ever searched for something on Google, then saw an ad for it on a web site?</p>
<p>What about Amazon?</p>
<p>Facebook?</p>
<p>Twitter?</p>
<p>eBay?</p>
<p>All of these companies use this tactic (called "retargeting" in ad industry parlance) but the worst part about it is not the relevant ads - that's actually a benefit to you - it's the massive amounts of data that these companies gather about you in the process: what sites you visit, when you use a web application (Hello, "Login with Facebook".), what purchases you're considering, what medications you may be taking, any health conditions you may have - the list goes on and on.</p>
<p>You can do some things to help protect your privacy - use a privacy-respecting search engine like DuckDuckGo, turn on "Do Not Track" in your browser, install ad blockers in your browser - but if you're really serious about preventing data exhaust, the best thing you can do is to use a different web browser for every site you visit.</p>
<p>Wait. What?! How is that even possible?!</p>
<p>It's not. There are too many web sites and not enough browsers to use this strategy. Plus, it would be a huge pain in the ass.</p>
<p>That's where <a href="https://support.mozilla.org/en-US/kb/containers" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Firefox Multi-Account Containers">Firefox Multi-Account Containers</a> ("Firefox Containers") come to the rescue.</p>
<h2>Firefox Multi-Account Containers</h2>
<p>From the Mozilla web site:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="msg msg--info"><a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/firefox/addon/multi-account-containers/">Multi-Account Containers</a> is a Firefox add-on that lets you separate your work, shopping or personal browsing without having to clear your history, log in and out, or use multiple browsers. Container tabs are like normal tabs except that the sites you visit will have access to a separate slice of the browser's storage. This means your site preferences, logged in sessions, and advertising tracking data won't carry over to the new container. Likewise, any browsing you do within the new container will not affect your logged in sessions, or tracking data of your other containers.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I discovered Firefox containers last year when I began diving back into Linux as it's the default browser installed in many Linux distributions.</p>
<p>Firefox has always been an excellent browser but over the years, I tended to use browsers that were faster (Safari) or had better plug-in support for the apps that I used (Chrome).</p>
<p>Firefox containers changed all of that.</p>
<p>Firefox is now the default browser on my personal machine, the browser I use for personal tasks on my work PC and even the default browser on my Android phone.</p>
<p>Here's how I configure and use Firefox containers. Feel free to follow along with me.</p>
<p>I'm assuming that you already have Firefox installed. If not, <a href="https://www.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/new/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Download Firefox">go ahead and do that</a>. Now, you're ready to get started with Firefox Multi-Account Containers.</p>
<p>First, you have to <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/multi-account-containers/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Download Firefox Multi-Account Containers">install the add-on from Mozilla</a> since it's not included by default. (It really should be.)</p>
<p>Once that's done, you'll see a new icon in your toolbar:</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/45/Screenshot-from-2020-04-26-07-20-31.png" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" srcset="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Screenshot-from-2020-04-26-07-20-31-xs.png 300w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Screenshot-from-2020-04-26-07-20-31-sm.png 480w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Screenshot-from-2020-04-26-07-20-31-md.png 768w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Screenshot-from-2020-04-26-07-20-31-lg.png 1024w"  alt="Firefox Multi-Account Containers Icon" width="227" height="90">
<figcaption >Firefox Multi-Account Containers Icon (Image Credit: me)</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Selecting it will show you some sample containers that have already been created for you to use or test. I haven't completed a fresh install of this plugin in awhile, but the starter containers are usually:</p>
<ul>
<li>Personal</li>
<li>Work</li>
<li>Banking</li>
<li>Shopping</li>
<li>Facebook</li>
<li>Twitter</li>
</ul>
<p>You can edit the name, color and icon to your liking. </p>
<p>(Ignore the "tmp" containers you see below, for now. I'll explain them shortly.)</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/45/Screenshot-from-2020-04-26-07-23-13.png" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" srcset="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Screenshot-from-2020-04-26-07-23-13-xs.png 300w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Screenshot-from-2020-04-26-07-23-13-sm.png 480w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Screenshot-from-2020-04-26-07-23-13-md.png 768w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/45/responsive/Screenshot-from-2020-04-26-07-23-13-lg.png 1024w"  alt="Firefox Multi-Account Containers Menu" width="319" height="593">
<figcaption >Firefox Multi-Account Containers Menu (Image Credit: me)</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>If you select "Personal" from this menu, it will launch a new Personal container.  Now, try this: visit any web site where you have an account, then login. (Not social media, yet.)</p>
<p>Next, create a new Default tab using the standard Firefox controls. ("Ctrl + T" on Linux and Windows, "Cmd + T" on a Mac or clicking the "+" icon in the toolbar). Now, visit that same web site again in the Default tab. You'll immediately notice that you're not logged in to the site in that tab.</p>
<p>That's because Firefox containers have (as the name implies) contained your activities for that web site within the Personal set of tabs (you can have as many container tabs open as your computer will allow). If this is a site that you login to frequently, you can check the box just below the page title in the Firefox containers menu, so that you can "Always open in Personal." By doing that, any time you launch a new tab and enter the URL for that web site, regardless of the container you're using, Firefox will load that web site in the Personal container automatically.</p>
<p>But wait - it gets better.</p>
<h2>The Facebook Container</h2>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/45/facebook_container_icon.png" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" srcset="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/45/responsive/facebook_container_icon-xs.png 300w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/45/responsive/facebook_container_icon-sm.png 480w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/45/responsive/facebook_container_icon-md.png 768w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/45/responsive/facebook_container_icon-lg.png 1024w"  alt="Facebook Container Fence Icon" width="160" height="27">
<figcaption >Facebook Container Fence Icon (Image Credit: me)</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Now, install the <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/facebook-container/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Facebook Container on Mozilla.org">Facebook Container</a> add-on. The Facebook Container is a special add-on that not only keeps your Facebook activity in the Firefox container, but it also blocks the loading of any Facebook cookies, code or off-site applications, such as "Share to Facebook" or "Login with Facebook."</p>
<p>Try it: open a tab in any other container, then visit any web site that has Facebook "Share" buttons. You'll see something like this. The tooltip text will load if you hover over the icon.</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-columns="1">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/45/gallery/facebook_container.png" data-size="1276x383"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/45/gallery/facebook_container-thumbnail.png" alt="Facebook Share Button Blocked" width="768" height="231"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">Facebook Share Button Blocked (Image Credit: Mozilla)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p>If the Facebook share button is served from Facebook.com, the Facebook Container will deactivate the button and prevent Facebook from knowing that you visited that site.</p>
<p>The same will happen if you visit a site that uses "Login with Facebook."</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-columns="1">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/45/gallery/allow_facebook.png" data-size="1275x617"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/45/gallery/allow_facebook-thumbnail.png" alt="Login with Facebook Blocked" width="768" height="372"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">Login with Facebook Blocked (Image Credit: Mozilla)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p>You always have the option of over-riding this setting by clicking the button but then, you'll be exposing your online activites to Facebook - but at least the choice is <em>yours</em>.</p>
<p>There are similar add-ons for <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/twitter-container/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Twitter Container Add-on on Mozilla">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/contain-amazon/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Amazon Container Add-on on Mozilla">Amazon</a>, <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/google-container/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Google Container Add-on on Mozilla">Google</a>, and other sites. I recommend you install as many of them as possible.</p>
<h2>The Default Tab</h2>
<p>I use keyboard shortcuts as much as possible. They enable me to accomplish things so much faster than navigating through application menus. So, if you're like me, that means you probably create tabs using "Ctrl + T" on Linux and Windows or "Cmd + T" on a Mac.</p>
<p>When you do this, you launch a Default tab (and related container) in Firefox. Doing this means that the more frequently you use the Default tab, you're more likely to expose your online activites across sites.</p>
<h3>Temporary Containers</h3>
<p>To solve his problem, install the <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/temporary-containers/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Temporary Containers Add-on on Mozilla">Temporary Containers</a> add-on. Next, go to the Add-ons menu item in Firefox, find Temporary Containers, select the ellipse menu, then select Preferences. This add-on is very configurable, but you don't need to worry about that. Select the checkbox for "Automatic Mode" then close that tab.</p>
<p>Automatic Mode, as defined by the add-on creator:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="msg msg--info">Instantly reopen new tabs in Temporary Containers. You might lose the first few already typed characters in the address bar when reopening takes too long, but it prevents new tabs from writing and reading cookies in the default container.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Now that the Temporary Containers tab is installed, any time you create a new tab using keyboard shortcuts or use the "+" icon on the toolbar, Firefox will create a new Temporary tab. When you close the tab, all of the cookies that were set in that tab will be deleted, erasing any trace of your visit to that site. </p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight "><strong>Note:</strong> unlike Private Windows, visits to sites in Temporary Containers will still show up in your browser history.</p>
<p>But what happens if you use a Temporary container and wind up on a site where you have an account and would like to be remembered? Right-click the current tab and select the "Reopen in Container" menu, then select your chosen container. You can then select the Firefox containers icon in the toolbar and check the box to always open that site in that container.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/45/reopen_in_container.gif" alt="Reopen in Container Animation" width="386" height="298">
<figcaption >Reopen in Container (Image Credit: me)</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2>Go Further</h2>
<p>If you'd like to take additional steps to protect your privacy (and speed up your web browsing in the process) I recommend installing the following add-ons:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/ublock-origin/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="uBlock Origin add-on on Mozilla">uBlock Origin</a></li>
<li><a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/ublock-origin/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Privacy Badger add-on on Mozilla">Privacy Badger</a></li>
</ul>
<p>uBlock Origin is a fast ad-blocker that is efficient with resources. It doesn't hog a lot of memory or noticeably slow down your computer.</p>
<p>Privacy Badger has some similar functionality, but it's main purpose is to automatically learn which sites are tracking you, then block them accordingly.</p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight "><strong>Note:</strong> like most ad blocking add-ons, these applications can sometimes prevent sites from working properly. If you find yourself in that situation, you can turn off uBlock Origin or Privacy Badger for that site while leaving them turned on for other sites you visit.</p>
<h2>In Conclusion or "Who has time for all this?"</h2>
<p>When I tell people about my use of Firefox Multi-Account Containers, inevitably, I receive questions like, "How long did it take you to set this up?" and "Who has time for all this?"</p>
<p>Set up is easy - you can follow the instructions I've provided above and be done in 5 minutes or less. However, at the start, you do need to think differently about how you use your browser, but that's a short learning curve.</p>
<p>Installing Temporary Containers helped me a lot here, since I no longer had to worry about accidentally opening something in a permanent Default container.</p>
<p>I suggest you give it a try. You'll notice a significant drop in the number of re-targeting ads that you receive and that's <strong>the</strong> key indicator that it's working.</p>
<p>If you find it too complicated for day-to-day use, you can always switch back to your usual browsing habits.</p>
<h2>Bonus: Protect Your Privacy on Your Smartphone</h2>
<p>Firefox on iOS doesn't support add-ons - and never will - due to Apple's strict software security model. On Android, the uBlock Origin and Privacy Badger add-ons can be installed, but not Firefox Multi-Account containers. (insert sad face here)</p>
<p>This can be problematic as it exposes the data exhaust from your mobile browsing, but there are other things you can do to help prevent that.</p>
<h3>Apps</h3>
<p>If you use any of the sites mentioned above, all of them have their own apps for your phone. If you need to buy something on Amazon or search for something on Google, use the site's respective app. Generally speaking, any activity in those apps stays in those apps.</p>
<p>My personal exception to this rule is Facebook. The Facebook app is notorious for not respecting privacy settings, like when you turn off Location Services for the app. Twitter is better, but still aggressive.</p>
<p>For these sites, I use a separate browser: I installed Brave, a browser that, like Firefox, also helps protect your privacy. The only two sites that I use in Brave?</p>
<p>Facebook and Twitter.</p>
<p>Those two sites both have very good mobile web experiences and are the only way I can be certain that they're not tracking my location or other web activities.</p>
<h3>Sensitive Searches</h3>
<p>I use DuckDuckGo for web searches on both my laptop and smartphone. While I trust DuckDuckGo to not track me all over the web, that doesn't mean that I trust the sites to which it links.</p>
<p>For this, I sometimes use the nuclear option for sensitive searches: <a href="https://www.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/mobile/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Firefox Focus on Mozilla">Firefox Focus</a>, a browser that clears everything from your device (including history) when the app is closed. It's available on both Android and iOS and, in practice, functions like the Temporary Containers add-on I described above.</p>
<p>I use this when I'm searching for things that I don't want anyone to attribute to me. For example, a new cholesterol medication or mortgage refinancing rates. The first search and subsequent site visits to the sites in the search results may expose the fact that I have high cholesterol (I don't) and that's health data that no one needs to know, other than my doctor. The second protects me from incessant retargeting by mortgage lenders and brokers.</p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Review: System76 Lemur Pro</title>
        <author>
            <name>John A. Federico</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://gadgetboy.org/review-system76-lemur-pro/"/>
        <id>https://gadgetboy.org/review-system76-lemur-pro/</id>

        <updated>2020-04-30T18:51:41-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/lemur.jpg" alt="Just a Lemur." />
                    I decided it was time to replace my aging 2015 MacBook Pro. Even&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/lemur.jpg" alt="Just a Lemur." />
                <p>I decided it was time to replace my aging 2015 MacBook Pro. Even though it's still in mint physical condition with a beautiful HiDPI ("Retina") display and is generally great to type on, the battery was beginning to show its age and it will become ineligible for OS upgrades in the near future.</p>
<p>I experimented with a Chromebook for a short while, then found myself <a href="https://gadgetboy.org/my-new-chromebook-isnt-a-chromebook-at-all/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">running Pop!_OS on a 13" Dell 2-in-1</a>, which I've enjoyed a lot. Using that machine has generally been a great experience, especially since Ubuntu seems to support all the hardware. My only complaint has been the trackpad - it's just not as precise as I'm used to and can be really frustrating to use. (It's not a Linux problem - it's the same running Windows 10.)</p>
<p>While immersing myself in some projects at home, I decided that I wanted a more powerful machine with a bigger, matte screen and a passable trackpad. After much deliberation, I bought a <a href="https://www.dell.com/en-us/shop/dell-laptops/new-inspiron-15-7000-laptop/spd/inspiron-15-7591-laptop" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Dell Inspiron 15 7591">Dell Inspiron 15 7591</a>. It's an awesome machine that's a joy to type on and, with a 32 GB RAM kit and NVIDIA Graphics, it's screaming fast. The trackpad is pretty damn good, too, and the aluminium shell feels and looks great. It supports two NVMe drives and yet another 2.5" mass storage drive (SSD, Hybrid or Hard Drive). It's a beautiful beast that won't break the bank.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/inspiron_7591.png" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" srcset="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/responsive/inspiron_7591-xs.png 300w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/responsive/inspiron_7591-sm.png 480w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/responsive/inspiron_7591-md.png 768w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/responsive/inspiron_7591-lg.png 1024w"  alt="Dell Inspiron 15 7591" width="1140" height="473">
<figcaption >Image Credit: Dell</figcaption>
</figure>
<p> </p>
<p>(Full Disclosure: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/johnfederico/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="John Federico on LinkedIn.com">I work for Dell</a> running software partnerships, making this post a little...uncomfortable to write. I'm not involved in the hardware side of the business in any way other than I can sometimes get my hands on some machines before they're released to the <a href="#mcetoc_1e5km0bsc0" title="Footnotes">public*</a>.) <span data-offset-key="7su1a-0-0">😉</span></p>
<p>I was generally in love with the 7591, but there was just one problem with it: I couldn't get it to properly run any flavor of Linux. Even though the machine is <a href="https://certification.ubuntu.com/hardware/201903-26880" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Dell Inspiron 15 7591 Ubuntu Certification">Ubuntu Certified</a> (which is a key reason I chose it), I couldn't get the PCI sound card to work. USB audio input and output both worked fine, but troubleshooting the built-in sound card was an exercise in frustration.</p>
<p>I think we all take for granted that our laptops can play sound until you find yourself trying to learn something from a YouTube video and have to switch to a different PC or your smartphone.</p>
<p>Since the machine didn't ship with Ubuntu pre-installed, I was unable to get support from Dell. Look, I get it: successfully supporting millions of consumers (many of them not very tech savvy) is no small feat. If you buy a new car, then completely replace the engine with something else, you can't expect the manufacturer to support it. This appears to be industry wide, not just at Dell. (Though, I will ask, why bother certifying a PC for Ubuntu if you're not going to support it with that OS? But, I digress...)</p>
<p>The Pop!_OS and Ubuntu communities are great resources, but I finally gave up after three weeks and sold it on eBay. The shop where I bought the 32 GB RAM kit won't accept returns unless the memory is DOA and I didn't feel like negotiating the restocking fee on the PC, nor create a support incident for the Dell support team to deal with - with so many people working from home now, they are likely overwhelmed. It was easier to just restore the Windows 10 OS factory image and sell it as "New, Open Box."</p>
<p>So, even as I returned to my 13" machine, I was trying to figure out my options. I didn't want to spend a ton of money on a PC that wasn't my daily driver, I wasn't willing to buy a similar machine and hope for a better trackpad and, most importantly, I didn't want to have to wrestle with a PC from any major OEM to get Linux running on it. Even users of Thinkpads, which are famously great for supporting Linux across the product line, were having issues getting Ubuntu to run properly on models that I would have considered.</p>
<p>I wanted a Linux machine with hardware support out of the box, but any device with Linux pre-installed from a major PC OEM is typically sold as a "<a href="#mcetoc_1e5km0bsc0" title="Footnote">Developer Edition*</a>," which means it's <a href="https://www.dell.com/en-us/work/shop/overview/cp/linuxsystems" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Dell Project Sputnik">built - and priced - for business use</a>.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/System76-System76_Logo_Blue-by_Kate_Hazen_of_System76.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" srcset="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/responsive/System76-System76_Logo_Blue-by_Kate_Hazen_of_System76-xs.jpg 300w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/responsive/System76-System76_Logo_Blue-by_Kate_Hazen_of_System76-sm.jpg 480w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/responsive/System76-System76_Logo_Blue-by_Kate_Hazen_of_System76-md.jpg 768w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/responsive/System76-System76_Logo_Blue-by_Kate_Hazen_of_System76-lg.jpg 1024w"  alt="System76 Branded Desktop Image" width="640" height="360"></figure>
<p>So, I started searching for other PC's with Linux pre-installed and, not surprisngly, System76 kept popping up with great reviews and a huge community of super fans. Of course, I knew of System76 as they're the creator and maintainer of Pop!_OS, but I was still thinking (hoping?) that I could get a better spec'd and more economical machine from Dell that would run Linux.</p>
<p>As I was overthinking the whole decision, I made my 3,000th visit to the Sytem76 web site so I could (again) configure a 15" <a href="https://system76.com/laptops/darter" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Darter Pro on System76.com">Darter Pro</a> machine and noticed that System76 was about to release a new PC - the 2020 14" <a href="https://system76.com/laptops/lemur" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Lemur Pro on System76.com">Lemur Pro</a>.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/lemur_pro.png" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" srcset="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/responsive/lemur_pro-xs.png 300w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/responsive/lemur_pro-sm.png 480w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/responsive/lemur_pro-md.png 768w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/responsive/lemur_pro-lg.png 1024w"  alt="Lemur Pro" width="952" height="582">
<figcaption >Image Credit: System76</figcaption>
</figure>
<p> </p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/lemur_pro_angles.png" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" srcset="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/responsive/lemur_pro_angles-xs.png 300w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/responsive/lemur_pro_angles-sm.png 480w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/responsive/lemur_pro_angles-md.png 768w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/responsive/lemur_pro_angles-lg.png 1024w"  alt="Lemur Pro from different angles" width="1327" height="769">
<figcaption >Image Credit: System76</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>In addition to all of the other benefits of a System76 machine (Disabled Intel ME, CoreBoot open source firmware, full Pop!_Os support, etc.) they were touting 14 hours of battery life, a 10th Gen Intel Core processor, a matte 1080p display and up to 40 GB of RAM in a slim, attractive PC with a modern, no-button trackpad.</p>
<p>I subscribed to the Early Access mailing list and put it out of my mind for awhile. (Probably only a day or so, if I'm being honest with myself.) About a week later, while I was literally dealing with the frustration of using the trackpad on my current machine, I received an email from System76 informing me that I could place one of the first orders for a Lemur Pro. (True to their word, only customers who showed early interest could configure and order one. Random web site visitors had to wait another day or so. That impressed me.)</p>
<p>I configured and ordered a Lemur Pro with 40 GB RAM and a 512 GB NVMe drive. (I can still add another NVMe drive, if I have a need for it.)</p>
<p>The next morning, I received both a friendly email and a phone call from System76, letting me know that my order was processed and that it was in the production queue. (Each System76 machine is built-to-order.) 24 hours later, I received another email message telling me that my machine was built and on its way to me via UPS.</p>
<p>My Lemur Pro arrived four days later. UPS required a signature for delivery but I was able to just flash my ID through the glass on our front door and the driver left it on the porch - a perfect COVID-19, no-contact delivery.</p>
<h2>Unboxing</h2>
<h3>First Impressions</h3>
<p>I'm not going to lie: when I was exploring Linux distros, one of the reasons I was attracted to Pop!_OS was the brand messaging, desktop graphics and overall user experience of the OS. I found their packaging to be consistent with that and right on-brand. </p>
<p>In what appears to be taking a queue from Apple, System76 ships the device secured in a reusable plastic-and-cardboard mechanism. It's worth keeping around in case you need to ship your machine for service or maybe want to sell it in the future.</p>
<p>The envelope containing System76 and Pop!_OS stickers was a nice touch.</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-columns="3">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_closed_box.jpg" data-size="3052x1824"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_closed_box-thumbnail.jpg" alt="System76 sealed box" width="768" height="459"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">System76 sealed box</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_box_unleash.jpg" data-size="2893x1796"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_box_unleash-thumbnail.jpg" alt="System76 box side closeup" width="768" height="477"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">System76 box side closeup</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_box_inside_cover.jpg" data-size="3284x1824"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_box_inside_cover-thumbnail.jpg" alt="System76 inside box cover" width="768" height="427"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">System76 inside box cover</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_lemur_pro_in_box.jpg" data-size="1824x2232"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_lemur_pro_in_box-thumbnail.jpg" alt="System76 inside box cover with Lemur Pro" width="768" height="940"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">System76 inside box cover with Lemur Pro</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_lemur_pro_packaging_front.jpg" data-size="4000x1824"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_lemur_pro_packaging_front-thumbnail.jpg" alt="System76 Lemur Pro packaging, front" width="768" height="350"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">System76 Lemur Pro packaging, front</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_lemur_pro_packaging_behind.jpg" data-size="4000x1824"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_lemur_pro_packaging_behind-thumbnail.jpg" alt="System76 Lemur Pro packaging, behind" width="768" height="350"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">System76 Lemur Pro packaging, behind</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_lemur_pro_power_supply_packaging.jpg" data-size="4000x1824"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_lemur_pro_power_supply_packaging-thumbnail.jpg" alt="System76 Lemur Pro power supply packaging" width="768" height="350"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">System76 Lemur Pro power supply packaging</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_lemur_pro_inside_box_bottom.jpg" data-size="4000x1824"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_lemur_pro_inside_box_bottom-thumbnail.jpg" alt="System76 Lemur Pro, inside bottom of box" width="768" height="350"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">System76 Lemur Pro, inside bottom of box</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_lemur_pro_bottom.jpg" data-size="3561x1814"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_lemur_pro_bottom-thumbnail.jpg" alt="System76 Lemur Pro bottom" width="768" height="391"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">System76 Lemur Pro bottom</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_lemur_pro_closed_1.jpg" data-size="4000x1824"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_lemur_pro_closed_1-thumbnail.jpg" alt="System76 Lemur Pro with lid closed" width="768" height="350"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">System76 Lemur Pro with lid closed</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_lemur_pro_opened.jpg" data-size="1824x2209"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_lemur_pro_opened-thumbnail.jpg" alt="System76 Lemur Pro opened" width="768" height="930"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">System76 Lemur Pro opened</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_lemur_pro_with_power_supply.jpg" data-size="1824x3174"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_lemur_pro_with_power_supply-thumbnail.jpg" alt="System76 Lemur Pro with power supply" width="768" height="1336"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">System76 Lemur Pro with power supply</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_lemur_pro_envelope.jpg" data-size="3419x1820"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_lemur_pro_envelope-thumbnail.jpg" alt="Lemur Pro with System76 branded envelope" width="768" height="409"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">Lemur Pro with System76 branded envelope</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_lemur_pro_envelope_opened.jpg" data-size="4000x1824"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_lemur_pro_envelope_opened-thumbnail.jpg" alt="Contents of the System76 branded envelope" width="768" height="350"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">Contents of the System76 branded envelope</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_welcome_card.jpg" data-size="1824x2502"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_welcome_card-thumbnail.jpg" alt="System76 Welcome Card" width="768" height="1053"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">System76 Welcome Card</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_lemur_pro_first_boot.jpg" data-size="1824x2119"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/system76_lemur_pro_first_boot-thumbnail.jpg" alt="System76 Lemur Pro first boot" width="768" height="892"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">System76 Lemur Pro first boot</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<h3>Weight &amp; Design</h3>
<p>The Lemur Pro is as powerful as the current MacBook Pro but weighs <em>less.</em> <strong>I</strong>t's also ligher than the current MacBook Air and even ligher than the amazing <a href="https://www.dell.com/en-us/shop/dell-laptops/new-xps-13-2-in-1-laptop/spd/xps-13-7390-2-in-1-laptop" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="XPS 7391 on Dell.com">XPS 13" 7391</a> that I use every day at work. (Though, to be fair, the 7391 is a 2-in-1 and has some added weight due to the touchscreen and sophisticated hinge mechanism.)</p>
<p>The Lemur Pro is so light that I can load both my work machine <em>and</em> my personal machine into my backpack and not even realize that I'm carrying two PC's. Even better, both machines can be powered by USC Type-C Power Delivery, so I only have to carry one charger. This will be great for business trips, when I want to work on personal projects after hours or watch movies on the plane.</p>
<p>The design is the same as what you would expect from any top-tier PC OEM. It has clean lines and relatively modern design touches. The System76 logo on the lid appears to be laser etched.</p>
<p>The biggest and most obvious design decision was the webcam. Rather than increase the size of the bezel, System76 decided to add a small bump above the screen to house the camera and built-in microphone. It's not distracting at all when using the machine, but obviously protrudes by a few millimeters when the lid is closed. I'm hoping that the chassis will adequately protect it during transit.</p>
<p>For some unknown reason, System76 made the decision to place the power button on the right<strong> side</strong> of the machine, not on the keyboard deck. Depending on your perspective, this could be a poor design choice, something to just get used to, or both.</p>
<p>During my first full day of using the Lemur Pro, I plugged-in a USB Type-C cable with Power Delivery and DisplayPort (which is on the left side) so that I could use it with my <a href="https://amzn.to/2K9NA6f" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Dell U3818DW">38" Dell display</a> to get some work done. Naturally, since the machine is so light, I braced it with my right hand and accidentally pushed the power button, putting it into Suspend mode. I definitely need to remember that in the future.</p>
<h3>Materials &amp; Build Quality</h3>
<p>At the time this post is written, System76 doesn't indicate what materials are used to build the Lemur Pro chassis on its web site. While looking at the photos during the buying process, I guessed that it was a nice, Thinkpad-like plastic or some kind of aluminum or magnesium alloy.</p>
<p>After it arrived, I realized it was metal but didn't know what kind, so I asked the System76 support team and they responded almost immediately:</p>
<blockquote>
<p class="msg msg--highlight ">Hello John,<br><br>Glad you're enjoying the Lemur Pro! The chassis is made out of Magnesium-Aluminum alloy: 9% Aluminum, 90% Magnesium, 1% other material. (Before you ask, I do not know what the "other material" is; I assume our supplier simply includes that as a tolerance.) Please let us know if you have any other questions! --Jacob</p>
</blockquote>
<p><em>Thanks, Jacob.</em></p>
<p>The Magnesium-Aluminum alloy is smooth to the touch and in my short time using it, appears to reject fingerprints. (Though, System76 includes a microfiber cloth with the system, so perhaps this is a premature observation.) It has tiny reflective flecks of material that only appear in the right light and from the right perspective. This may be a conscious design choice or just a natural charateristic of the alloy. Those flecks might also be the "1% other material" but I'm just guessing.</p>
<p>Fit and finish are excellent with no visible gaps or imperfections. There is no flexing of the chassis or the keyboard deck - it's a solid typing experience. In fact, it's one of the best keyboards I've used in a long time, almost on par with my 2015 MacBook Pro.</p>
<p>The bottom panel flexes a wee bit but it doesn't detract from the overall build quality of the machine. I've only noticed it when I close the lid and grip the PC with one hand.</p>
<p>The 14.1" 1080p screen has a matte finish and is bright, crisp and seemingly color accurate. The Lemur Pro's screen is pleasingly larger than my 13" devices and the form factor is just about perfect.</p>
<p class="msg msg--info">Even though it would be nice to have a larger screen on-the-go, I recently discovered that the tradeoffs of a 15.6" machine just aren't worth it - especially the keyboard layout.</p>
<p class="msg msg--info">I don't understand why just about every PC OEM feels the need to fill the keyboard deck of larger devices with a number pad, shifting the trackpad and keyboard to the left. It's an awkward experience. Instead of the number pad, why not center the keyboard and add front-firing speakers on each side or maybe just a fingerprint reader that <em>actually works</em> more than 20% of the time? Anyone who really needs a number pad can get one from <a href="https://amzn.to/2XENFXu" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="USB Numbers Pads on Amazon.com">Amazon for less than $20</a>.</p>
<h4>Trackpad</h4>
<p>The trackpad on this machine is excellent. Is it as good as a MacBook Pro or a Dell XPS? Not quite, but it's pretty damn close. The fact that it doesn't have buttons is a real plus.</p>
<h4>Power Supply</h4>
<p>From the perspective of portability, the power supply is great. It's relatively small and lightweight and gets the job done. And while System76 definitely considered the needs of road warriors and hallway walkers with the Lemur Pro's great battery life, they missed the mark with the power supply. The total length of the cables is so ridiculously short, it's almost comical. I'm going to have carry an extension cord or find a longer main lead with the right connector for the power supply.</p>
<p>Everything else about the device is so well thought out that this decision left me scratching my head.</p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight "><strong>Update:</strong> Right now, I'm using a spare power cord from a Sonos speaker that's 6 feet long for the main lead, but you can replace it with a <a href="https://amzn.to/3cw9FrE" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Non-Polarized 10ft AC Power Cord">high quality, non-polarized cord for around $8 USD</a>.</p>
<h3>Performance</h3>
<p>First, let's look at the specs of my particular configuration, outlined in the table below.</p>
<table data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<tbody data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<tr data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<td data-v-7b22f3a8=""><strong>Operating System</strong></td>
<td data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<p>Pop!_OS 19.10 (64-bit)</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<td data-v-7b22f3a8=""><strong>Firmware</strong></td>
<td data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<p>System76 Open Firmware (Coreboot, EDK2, System76 Firmware Apps)</p>
<p>System76 Open Source Embedded Controller Firmware</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<td data-v-7b22f3a8=""><strong>Processor</strong></td>
<td data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<p>10th Gen Intel® Core i7-10510U<strong>:</strong> 1.8 GHz (up to 4.9 GHz burst mode) - 8MB Cache - 4 Cores - 8 Threads (<em>upgraded from i5</em>)</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<td data-v-7b22f3a8=""><strong>Display</strong></td>
<td data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<p>14.1″ 1920×1080 FHD, Matte Finish</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<td data-v-7b22f3a8=""><strong>Graphics</strong></td>
<td data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<p>Intel® UHD Graphics</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<td data-v-7b22f3a8=""><strong>Memory</strong></td>
<td data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<p>40 GB DDR4 @ 2666 MHz</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<td data-v-7b22f3a8=""><strong>Storage</strong></td>
<td data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<p>1× M.2 NVMe SSD @ 512 GB</p>
<p>Sequential Read Speed: 3,500 MB/s, Sequential Write Speed: 3,200 MB/s</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<td data-v-7b22f3a8=""><strong>Expansion</strong></td>
<td data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<p>USB 3.1 Type-C, 2× USB 3.0 Type-A, MicroSD Card Reader</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<td data-v-7b22f3a8=""><strong>Input</strong></td>
<td data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<p>Multitouch Clickpad, Backlit US QWERTY Keyboard</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<td data-v-7b22f3a8=""><strong>Networking</strong></td>
<td data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<p>Intel® Wireless-AC Wi-Fi, Bluetooth</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<td data-v-7b22f3a8=""><strong>Video Ports</strong></td>
<td data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<p>HDMI, USB 3.1 Type-C w/ DisplayPort</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<td data-v-7b22f3a8=""><strong>Audio</strong></td>
<td data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<p>Stereo Speakers, 1× Headphone/Microphone Combo (TRRS)</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<td data-v-7b22f3a8=""><strong>Camera</strong></td>
<td data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<p>720p HD Webcam</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<td data-v-7b22f3a8=""><strong>Security</strong></td>
<td data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<p>Disabled Intel ME, Kensington® Lock</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<td data-v-7b22f3a8=""><strong>Battery</strong></td>
<td data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<p>Li-Ion - 73 Wh</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<td data-v-7b22f3a8=""><strong>Charger</strong></td>
<td data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<p>65 W, AC-in 100–240 V, 50–60 Hz</p>
<p>65W+ USB Type-C Charging Compatible</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<td data-v-7b22f3a8=""><strong>Dimensions</strong></td>
<td data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<p>12.64″ × 8.5″ × 0.61″ (32.1 × 21.6 × 1.55 cm)</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<td data-v-7b22f3a8=""><strong>Weight</strong></td>
<td data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<p>2.2 lbs (.99kg)</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<td data-v-7b22f3a8=""><strong>Warranty</strong></td>
<td data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<p>1 Year</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<td data-v-7b22f3a8=""><strong>Price as configured</strong></td>
<td data-v-7b22f3a8="">
<p>$1,688 + $32 for UPS Ground shipping</p>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h4>First Boot</h4>
<p>I chose to capture the unboxing in photos and not video as my other cameras and tripods are in storage at the moment. So, when it came to booting the machine for the first time, I wanted to snap a few photos of the process.</p>
<p>The Lemur Pro boots so fast that I couldn't even unlock my phone quickly enough to take a picture! In seconds, the machine booted into system setup.</p>
<p>If you've ever installed Pop!_OS on your machine, the experience of having it installed on a new PC is exactly the same as booting from a live session: select your country, keyboard layout, disk encryption preference, etc. When it's done, it will ask you to create a user, after a restart.</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-columns="1">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/neofetch.png" data-size="801x454"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/neofetch-thumbnail.png" alt="neofetch on my System76 Lemur Pro" width="768" height="435"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">neofetch on my System76 Lemur Pro (Image Credit: me)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<h4>Processor &amp; GPU</h4>
<p>The CPU is a 10th Generation Intel i7 processor (an upgrade from the 10th Gen i5 in the base model Lemur Pro) in the "U" spec, which indicates that it's designed for Ultrabooks that require longer battery life. Spec-for-spec, it certainly doesn't pack the horespower of the Dell Inspiron 7591 I gave up.</p>
<p class="msg msg--info">The Dell Inspiron 7591 has a 9th Gen Intel i7 in the "H" spec (high performance) with 6 cores - 12 threads, 12 MB cache and burst mode up to 4.5 GHz. More importantly, it has a dedicated NVIDIA GPU which helps render video faster. (And improves gaming performance, but I'm not much of a gamer.)</p>
<p>With that said, the Lemur Pro defintely punches above its weight. It's surprisingly fast for its specs and the onboard Intel GPU works well, powering both the built-in display and my <a href="https://amzn.to/3cwwFXN" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Dell U3818DW Curved Display">large (3840 x 1600) external display</a> simultaneously. Video playback and video conferences are smooth and consistent.</p>
<p>It quickly renders web pages in Firefox, which is typically a small step behind the speed of the Chromium and WebKit rendering engines.</p>
<p><strong>GeekBench</strong></p>
<p>Running Geekbench5, the Lemur Pro scored better in Multi-core tests than the Intel 8th Gen U series processor in a Dell Inspiron 7386, but lower in Single-core tests. You can see the full results of the Lemur Pro test <a href="https://browser.geekbench.com/v5/cpu/1817319" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="GeekBench Scores for the System76 Lemur Pro">here</a> and the Dell test <a href="https://browser.geekbench.com/v5/cpu/1717304" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="GeekBench 5 test results for the Dell Inspiron 7386">here</a>.</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-columns="1">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/geekbench.png" data-size="886x143"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/geekbench-thumbnail.png" alt="GeekBench5 results on my System76 Lemur Pro" width="768" height="124"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">GeekBench5 results on my System76 Lemur Pro</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p>Here's the obiligatory screenshot of HTOP running in a terminal window. I was running the following apps:</p>
<ul>
<li>Firefox (at least 20 tabs &amp; windows)</li>
<li>Zoom</li>
<li>Pidgin</li>
<li>Visual Studio Code</li>
<li>Microsoft Teams</li>
<li>Slack</li>
<li>Publii</li>
<li>Signal</li>
<li>Flameshot</li>
</ul>
<div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-columns="1">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/htop.png" data-size="1425x850"><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/gallery/htop-thumbnail.png" alt="HTOP on my System76 Lemur Pro" width="768" height="458"></a>
<figcaption class="gallery-description">HTOP on my System76 Lemur Pro (Image Credit: me)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
<p><strong>Thermals</strong></p>
<p>On a few occasions, the fans spun up like jet engines, then quickly went silent. During those instances, I was installing multiple package updates from Pop!_Shop or running a video conference in Zoom.</p>
<p>Otherwise, the machine runs quite cool. I can barely feel any excess heat when it's on my lap during general use. (I'm sure I might have a different experience if I was rendering a 4K video with compositing while sitting on the couch.)</p>
<h4>RAM</h4>
<p>Do I really need 40 GB of RAM for a machine that I'm using for hobby projects?</p>
<p>Generally, no.</p>
<p>While I do some light video production, photo editing and vector art production, I use my machine mostly for office work, Raspberry Pi and other SBC projects, managing my home lab and testing home automation scripts. </p>
<p>But I want to <strong>fly</strong> through my workflows. When I'm in The Zone, I don't want to deal with a lagging OS. Having excess memory ensures that the OS almost never has to write anything to the swap partition on the disk. (Also referred to as "Virtual RAM." <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virtual_memory" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Virtual RAM on Wikipedia">Wikipedia</a>)</p>
<p>Plus, maxing out the RAM ensures that the machine will have a long service life without much effort, and the additional memory improves its resale value should I decide to upgrade to a new machine in the future.</p>
<h4>Storage</h4>
<p>My preferred configuration is to have a small (&lt;250 GB) NVMe drive for the OS and a second, larger NVMe drive for my /home directory and files. However, after lots of shopping around, it doesn't appear that the smaller NVMe drives even come close to the performance of those that are 500 GB or larger, which is an important consideration for the OS drive.</p>
<p>With that in mind, I selected the smallest, fastest NVMe drive available during system configuration for both the OS and my files - <a href="https://amzn.to/2VchDk4" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Samsung EVO Pro">a 512 GB Samsung EVO Pro</a>. I could have gotten a 1 TB drive with the same read/write specs, but most of my larger media files are stored on NAS on my LAN, and in the cloud. I can upgrade to a larger drive or add a second drive at a later time, if I need it.</p>
<h4>Networking</h4>
<p>The Lemur Pro uses the onboard Intel networking controller with the 802.11ac spec and speeds up to 867 Mbps. I have other machines with 802.11ac but this feels much snappier, perhaps because web pages render so quickly. File transfers over SAMBA, SFTP, NFS and HTTPS also seem very fast.</p>
<h4>Battery Life</h4>
<p>If you've read this far, you know that I am not a professional PC reviewer so I had to improvise the battery life evaluation.</p>
<p>Here's what I did:</p>
<p>I unplugged the machine from the power supply and spent 4 hours writing this post, responding to email, watching YouTube tutorials on how to optimize OpenMediaVault and NextCloud, downloading software, and connecting with friends and family on social media.</p>
<p>I didn't do any video rendering or stream a ton of HD video, and I didn't compile any code. Basically, I just used it like an average consumer.</p>
<p>At the end of the 4 hours, my battery was at 91%. Pop!_OS indicated that I still had over 20 hours of use. The Pop!_OS power management profile was set to "Balanced."</p>
<p>It's not a scientific benchmark, but it should give you some idea about the battery life of the Lemur Pro: it's remarkable.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/power_after_4_hours.png" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" srcset="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/responsive/power_after_4_hours-xs.png 300w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/responsive/power_after_4_hours-sm.png 480w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/responsive/power_after_4_hours-md.png 768w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/43/responsive/power_after_4_hours-lg.png 1024w"  alt="Power Indicator after 4 hours" width="327" height="445">
<figcaption >Power indicator after 4 hours of use. (Image Credit: me)</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Eventually, I'll get a feel for how the battery life holds up under heavier loads.</p>
<h2>Final Thoughts</h2>
<p>I provided my opinion of this laptop based on my specific needs using my own decision making criteria. However, I'm hoping that based on my experience, you can get a sense of how well it might work for you.</p>
<h3>Positives:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Premium specs, look and feel</li>
<li>Light, Magnesium-Alloy chassis</li>
<li>Bright, color-accurate, matte-finish 1080p screen </li>
<li>Solid keyboard with good key travel</li>
<li>Ample ports</li>
<li>USB Type-C Power Delivery with Display Port</li>
<li>Powerful CPU that runs cool during general use</li>
<li>Quiet fans</li>
<li>Excellent trackpad performance</li>
<li>Pop!_OS (of course)</li>
<li><em>Complete hardware support</em> for Pop!_OS</li>
<li>An envelope full of cool stickers <span data-offset-key="7su1a-0-0">😉</span></li>
</ul>
<h3>Neutrals:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Slight chassis flex in certain use cases</li>
<li>Camera bump on the top screen bezel</li>
</ul>
<h3>Negatives:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Poorly placed power button</li>
<li>The power supply cables are waaayyy too short</li>
</ul>
<p class="msg msg--success">Overall, I'm extremely satisfied with my purchase of the Lemur Pro and am now wondering why I didn't buy a System76 machine sooner.</p>
<p>Do you have a Lemur Pro? Do you want one? Do you have specific questions about things I didn't cover?</p>
<p>Let me know in the comments or on <a href="https://twitter.com/gadgetboy" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="@gadgetboy on twitter">Twitter</a>.</p>
<p>---</p>
<h6>Footnotes</h6>
<p>* If you have the budget and you're looking for a machine pre-installed with Ubuntu, you owe it to yourself to explore a <a href="https://www.dell.com/en-us/work/shop/overview/cp/linuxsystems#tab-2" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Dell XPS 13 Developer Edition">Dell XPS 13 or 15 Developer Edition</a>. I had the privilege of getting to play with the new XPS 13 at CES this year and it's nothing short of amazing.</p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>What I did on my Holiday Staycation, 2020 Edition</title>
        <author>
            <name>John A. Federico</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://gadgetboy.org/what-i-did-on-my-holiday-staycation-2020-edition/"/>
        <id>https://gadgetboy.org/what-i-did-on-my-holiday-staycation-2020-edition/</id>
            <category term="YAML"/>
            <category term="Internet of Things"/>
            <category term="Home Automation"/>
            <category term="Home Assistant"/>
            <category term="Coding"/>

        <updated>2020-03-13T12:50:11-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/3/staycation_postcard.jpeg" alt="Staycation" />
                    I’m very fortunate. I work for a company that closes down for&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/3/staycation_postcard.jpeg" alt="Staycation" />
                <p>I’m very fortunate. I work for a company that closes down for the holidays, from December 25th to January 2nd.</p>
<p>For me, this is a period of decompression. Not just because <strong><em>I</em></strong> have the time off from work, but because <strong><em>all of my colleagues</em></strong> do, as well. There’s no pressure to check email every day and, should anything urgent pop-up during that period, people can always text me.</p>
<p>But mostly, in addition to spending time with family and friends, I take this time to learn new things and to tinker – activities I rarely have time to do throughout the year.</p>
<p>Here’s this year’s list.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>I <a href="https://gadgetboy.org/alarming-news/" title="Alarming News">installed</a> a <a rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label="Ring Alarm System (opens in a new tab)" href="https://amzn.to/2ZSQjYJ" target="_blank">Ring Alarm System</a> </strong>that included the <a rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label="Ring Alarm Retrofit Kit (opens in a new tab)" href="https://amzn.to/35oIjjw" target="_blank">Ring Alarm Retrofit Kit</a> and the existing home security wiring. I learned a lot about home security wiring and, more importantly, how the home security market is being disrupted by the Internet of Things (IoT).</li>
<li>I kicked my <a rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label="Vera Edge (opens in a new tab)" href="https://amzn.to/2Qo1c1F" target="_blank">Vera Edge</a> home controller to the curb and <strong>built a new home automation system from scratch</strong> using the open source <a rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label="Home Assistant (opens in a new tab)" href="https://www.home-assistant.io" target="_blank">Home Assistant</a> software, a <a rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label="Raspberry Pi 4 (opens in a new tab)" href="https://amzn.to/2QL4riJ" target="_blank">Raspberry Pi 4</a> and a <a rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label="GoControl HUSBZB-1 (opens in a new tab)" href="https://amzn.to/2SUbeJv" target="_blank">GoControl HUSBZB-1</a>. (Full post to come.)</li>
<li><strong>I started learning <a rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label="YAML (opens in a new tab)" href="https://yaml.org/" target="_blank">YAML</a>.</strong> Even though you don’t have to break out a programmers text editor to use Home Assistant, if you want to create more complex automations or get very specific in how you configure the user interface, you have to use YAML. This also helped me in my next endeavor.</li>
<li><strong>I learned how to manage <a rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label="Ruby (opens in a new tab)" href="https://www.ruby-lang.org" target="_blank">Ruby</a> packages</strong> so that I could <strong>install and configure <a rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label="Jekyll (opens in a new tab)" href="https://jekyllrb.com/" target="_blank">Jekyll</a> </strong>to publish this blog. (Full post to come) Jekyll helps you build static sites so they are <em>really</em> fast and, most importantly, <strong>unhackable</strong>. I’ve had way too many WordPress instances get hacked and fixing them was a major PITA. Jekyll is also configured using YAML. <br><br>Do I really need to do this? I mean, a basic blog on WordPress.com is cheap, fast and reliable. <br><br>Of course not. I just want to learn something new. <br><br>Once I figure out how to customize Jekyll themes and import posts from WordPress, I’ll probably host the files on <a rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label="GitHub Pages (opens in a new tab)" href="https://pages.github.com/" target="_blank">GitHub Pages</a>. I’ve been considering running the static site from a <a rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label="Raspberry Pi 2 B (opens in a new tab)" href="https://amzn.to/2ZSV9Fn" target="_blank">Raspberry Pi 2 B</a> on my home network, but this might be more trouble than it’s worth. I ran out of time during this holiday break, so getting this working will take a little longer.</li>
</ol>
<p>What did you learn this year?</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Alarming News</title>
        <author>
            <name>John A. Federico</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://gadgetboy.org/alarming-news/"/>
        <id>https://gadgetboy.org/alarming-news/</id>
            <category term="Internet of Things"/>
            <category term="Home Automation"/>

        <updated>2020-04-18T08:03:29-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/4/sirens.png" alt="Sirens" />
                    Before moving our family to Austin, we lived in Maplewood, NJ where&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/4/sirens.png" alt="Sirens" />
                <p>Before moving our family to Austin, we lived in <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/place/Maplewood,+NJ+07040/@40.7298131,-74.2836195,14z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m5!3m4!1s0x89c3ac591c878dfb:0x71f900089a81168b!8m2!3d40.7312956!4d-74.2707509" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label="Maplewood, NJ (opens in a new tab)">Maplewood, NJ</a> where we owned a 110-year old home. It’s a beautiful house with original mahogany mouldings, unique pine flooring and a gorgeous wrap-around porch.</p>
<p>But, it also had a basement that was full of water after Hurricane Sandy, a kitchen from the 80’s (until we renovated before selling), knob-and-tube wiring and plaster walls.</p>
<p>Modernizing it was a money-losing battle.</p>
<p>Knowing that, you can probably understand why we were ecstatic when we moved into our new home in Austin.</p>
<p>Because it was new.</p>
<p>Just built.</p>
<p>Never lived in.</p>
<p>By anyone.</p>
<p>And it has a modern, open concept layout with modern construction and amenities. Things like energy efficient windows, central air conditioning, a sprinkler system for the lawn and a home security system.</p>
<p>When we lived in Maplewood, I tried an after-market home security system almost 15 years ago. It never worked properly and installation required sticking chunky white pieces of plastic on every door and window. I cancelled the service and tossed it all.</p>
<p>Based on that experience, it was nice to have the house pre-wired with hidden (or barely visible) alarm contacts everywhere. Better still, if we have it professionally monitored, we receive a discount on our homeowners insurance.</p>
<p>Something about it bugged me, though.</p>
<p>I mean, WE LIVE IN THE FUTURE, where everything is “smart” and networked, yet the home security system they installed in our house is the same technology that’s been in use <a rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label="since it was invented in 1853 (opens in a new tab)" href="https://homesecurity.net/history/" target="_blank"><strong>since it was invented in 1853</strong></a>. Seriously – you can buy <a rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)" href="https://www.dsc.com/alarm-security-products/PC1616%20-%20PowerSeries%20Control%20Panel%20PC1616/1" target="_blank">one of these units</a> on eBay for $60.</p>
<p>It can only be programmed and managed through its <a rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label="archaic keypad (opens in a new tab)" href="https://www.dsc.com/index.php?n=Products&amp;o=view&amp;id=1278" target="_blank">archaic keypad</a>. There are no DIY instructions. (So that they can protect their installer network.) It has no remote access controls and has to be wired for monitoring via a 2G cellular modem since we don’t have old school telephone service, only internet over fiber.</p>
<p>So when Amazon presented its 2019 product showcase, as far as I’m concerned, the most interesting thing they announced wasn’t the <a rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label="Amazon Smart Oven (opens in a new tab)" href="https://amzn.to/2PEku1c" target="_blank">Amazon Smart Oven</a> or the new <a rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label="Echo Buds (opens in a new tab)" href="https://amzn.to/2YFJXvk" target="_blank">Echo Buds</a>.</p>
<p>It was the <a href="https://amzn.to/35j2rUG" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)">Ring Retrofit Alarm Kit</a>.</p>
<p>This magical device lets you connect your existing wired home security system to a <a rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)" href="https://amzn.to/2PgrXED" target="_blank">Ring Alarm Base Station</a>*. From there, you can get professional monitoring  over the internet – with LTE cellular backup – and control the entire system via the <a rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label="Ring mobile app (opens in a new tab)" href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/ring-always-home/id926252661" target="_blank">Ring mobile app</a>, including arming, disarming, guest access and panic mode.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/4/ring_alarm_mobile_app.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" srcset="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/4/responsive/ring_alarm_mobile_app-xs.jpg 300w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/4/responsive/ring_alarm_mobile_app-sm.jpg 480w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/4/responsive/ring_alarm_mobile_app-md.jpg 768w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/4/responsive/ring_alarm_mobile_app-lg.jpg 1024w"  alt="" width="1024" height="697">
<figcaption >Ring Alarm Mobile App (Image Credit: Ring)</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>You can also add wireless accessories like <a href="https://amzn.to/34lNr7x" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label="motion sensors (opens in a new tab)">motion sensors</a> and <a href="https://amzn.to/36EA0B7" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label="keypads (opens in a new tab)">keypads</a>.</p>
<p>Every component is either battery powered or has battery backup. If, for whatever reason, a thief decides that our home is an attractive target and figures out how to cut the power, the entire system still functions. If said thief decides to cut the internet connection, the system will still send triggers over LTE. (Backup and redundancy are your friends.)</p>
<p>I installed the <a rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://amzn.to/2PgrXED" target="_blank">Ring Alarm Base Station</a> before the Retrofit Alarm Kit arrived, which was simple.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/4/ring_base_station.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" srcset="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/4/responsive/ring_base_station-xs.jpg 300w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/4/responsive/ring_base_station-sm.jpg 480w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/4/responsive/ring_base_station-md.jpg 768w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/4/responsive/ring_base_station-lg.jpg 1024w"  alt="Ring Alarm Base Station" width="1024" height="683">
<figcaption >Ring Alarm Base Station (Image Credit: Ring)</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>I hid the base station (which also acts as the primary siren) behind some picture frames on the entertainment center in the living room and added a second <a rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label="wireless keypad (opens in a new tab)" href="https://amzn.to/36EA0B7" target="_blank">wireless keypad</a> by the backdoor so that I don’t have to run to the front of the house to disarm the system when my 14-year-old Cocker Spaniel needs to go outside in the middle of the night. (She’s a senior dog. I have to move quickly to get her out or things can get messy.)</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/4/ring_keypad.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" srcset="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/4/responsive/ring_keypad-xs.jpg 300w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/4/responsive/ring_keypad-sm.jpg 480w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/4/responsive/ring_keypad-md.jpg 768w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/4/responsive/ring_keypad-lg.jpg 1024w"  alt="Ring Alarm Keypad" width="1024" height="683">
<figcaption >Ring Alarm Keypad (Image Credit: Ring)</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Next, I added a <a rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)" href="https://shop.ring.com/collections/accessories/products/dome-siren" target="_blank">Dome Siren</a> to ensure that anyone on the second floor can also hear the alarm and a second <a rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)" href="https://amzn.to/2E9wBhk" target="_blank">motion sensor</a> to cover the front and garage doors.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/4/dome_siren.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" srcset="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/4/responsive/dome_siren-xs.jpg 300w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/4/responsive/dome_siren-sm.jpg 480w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/4/responsive/dome_siren-md.jpg 768w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/4/responsive/dome_siren-lg.jpg 1024w"  alt="" width="1024" height="795">
<figcaption >Dome Siren for Ring (Image Credit: Ring)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="post__image post__image" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/4/ring_motion_sensor.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" srcset="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/4/responsive/ring_motion_sensor-xs.jpg 300w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/4/responsive/ring_motion_sensor-sm.jpg 480w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/4/responsive/ring_motion_sensor-md.jpg 768w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/4/responsive/ring_motion_sensor-lg.jpg 1024w"  alt="Ring Motion Sensor" width="1024" height="683">
<figcaption >Ring Motion Sensor (Image Credit: Ring)</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2>Truly Alarming</h2>
<p>While I’m pretty comfortable with most tech, I had a momentary loss of confidence when reading the product page for the Retrofit Kit on Ring.com and opted for professional installation via <a rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)" href="https://www.ontechsmartservices.com/" target="_blank">OnTech</a>.</p>
<p>That was a huge mistake.</p>
<p>After showing up an hour later than than the allotted window, the installer – a nice, young man in his early 20’s – had <strong>no idea</strong> what he was doing. He’d never installed one of these before and had <strong>only watched a YouTube video</strong>. I immediately lost confidence.</p>
<p>And, boy, was I right.</p>
<p>Step number one in any job like this: label all your wires before you pull everything apart. Even though there were supposed to be six zones, he labelled only three wires – and they were all labelled incorrectly. In fact, he installed the <strong>AC power</strong> and <strong>siren</strong> connections as zones. (Thankfully, I had already disconnected the power or he would have fried the unit.)</p>
<p>I had to remove the old alarm system while he was <strong>reading the documentation on his phone</strong> and talking to his manager because he thought he was going to install a <strong>wireless</strong> system in the existing steel box. <strong>Nothing</strong> about the Retrofit Kit worked when he left. His “manager was going to call me to reschedule” but that never happened.</p>
<p>I contacted them for a refund and they were supposed to get back to me “in the morning.” That also never happened. I finally disputed the charge with my credit card issuer.</p>
<p>The next day, I ended up pulling apart his mess and installing the system myself. It took me about an hour. But what I discovered during the installation process <strong>really</strong> pissed me off.</p>
<p>When we bought the house, the alarm was pre-installed during construction. (The best time to do it, natch.) The installers wired everything to a <a rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label="DSC PC1616 (opens in a new tab)" href="https://www.dsc.com/index.php?n=products&amp;o=view&amp;id=1" target="_blank">DSC PC1616</a> – a six zone alarm system. However, there are <strong>20</strong> wired zones. They spliced numerous zones into single zone ports on the alarm system and just labelled them “Garage-Office-Dining Room-Back Door.”</p>
<p>It was a total clusterf*ck.</p>
<p>First, because it was a <strong>hack</strong> and second, because the Ring Retrofit Alarm Kit runs on Lithium batteries – and there isn’t nearly enough power to activate and monitor multiple zones on a single circuit.</p>
<p>Since each Retrofit Alarm Kit only has eight zones, I ended up having to buy a second unit so that I could properly wire each zone. For those of you doing the math at home, yes, there will be a few zones that aren’t wired, but all of them require a thirty-foot ladder to get near them, so I feel comfortable leaving them that way, for now. I may grab a third unit when they go on sale in the future, just to make sure all zones are wired.</p>
<h2>Finishing Touches</h2>
<p>My final configuration will be to <a rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)" href="https://support.ring.com/hc/en-us/articles/360028205592-Using-Alexa-Guard-with-Alarm-to-Detect-Broken-Glass-Smoke-and-Carbon-Monoxide" target="_blank">set up our Echo devices with Alexa Guard to act as glass break, smoke and carbon monoxide sensors</a>. (We own five Echo Dots and a Sonos Play One, though only the Echo devices support this feature.) This is a huge bonus – I don’t have to buy any additional hardware** to let the monitoring station know which sensor is triggered. If no one responds to the safety check, they’ll simply send the appropriate emergency service to the house.</p>
<p>My favorite part of the whole set up is the remote access. We can now arm and disarm every sensor in the system from our smartphones wherever we are and also grant access to friends and family by giving them a temporary passcode. The convenience is great.</p>
<p>The icing on the proverbial cake?</p>
<p>The professional monitoring from Ring is half the cost of monitoring from my existing service provider – and I didn’t have to pay extra for the cellular hardware. The purchase of the Ring products will almost pay for themselves in the <s>first</s> second year and the system includes all the convenience we’ve been waiting for.</p>
<p>I’ll unload the old system on eBay or Facebook Marketplace.</p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator">
<h4>Footnotes</h4>
<p>*Only 8 zones are supported.</p>
<p>**If you don’t have an Echo device, you can purchase <a rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label="a sensor that will listen for your smoke or CO alarms (opens in a new tab)" href="https://amzn.to/35l5LyL" target="_blank">a sensor that will listen for your smoke or CO alarms</a> and send the appropriate trigger to the monitoring station.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Keto Update</title>
        <author>
            <name>John A. Federico</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://gadgetboy.org/keto-update/"/>
        <id>https://gadgetboy.org/keto-update/</id>
            <category term="Keto"/>
            <category term="Fitness Training"/>
            <category term="Fitness"/>

        <updated>2020-03-11T21:12:55-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/6/keto.jpg" alt="Keto" />
                    Two months ago, I took the plunge and changed to a Ketogenic&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/6/keto.jpg" alt="Keto" />
                <p>Two months ago, I took the plunge and <a href="https://gadgetboy.org/2019/10/27/going-keto/">changed to a Ketogenic diet</a>. Here are my observations, so far.</p>
<ul>
<li>You can find a Keto meal in most places – but not everywhere. Be sure to check the menu before you decide to eat out. My wife and I went to a really great place for dinner to celebrate our anniversary and there’s was barely anything that I could make work with my diet.</li>
<li>You have to keep things interesting. Sure, it’s great to have some go-to meals to prepare but you have to keep exploring new recipes or you will get bored.</li>
<li>Avocados are your friend.</li>
<li>I haven’t lost any weight, but I have lost inches. I had to buy new, smaller jeans and many of my favorite shirts now fit again. I’ve started intermittent fasting to see if that will help kick start things.</li>
<li>My endurance during CrossFit has been much improved. I’m able to complete most workouts without having to stop to catch my breath or deal with the usual stitch in my side (caused by irregular, intense breathing.).</li>
</ul>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>My New Chromebook isn&#x27;t a Chromebook, at all.</title>
        <author>
            <name>John A. Federico</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://gadgetboy.org/my-new-chromebook-isnt-a-chromebook-at-all/"/>
        <id>https://gadgetboy.org/my-new-chromebook-isnt-a-chromebook-at-all/</id>
            <category term="Windows 10"/>
            <category term="Windows"/>
            <category term="Ubuntu"/>
            <category term="System76"/>
            <category term="Productivity"/>
            <category term="Pop!_OS"/>
            <category term="MacBook"/>
            <category term="Mac"/>
            <category term="Linux"/>
            <category term="Gadgets"/>
            <category term="Chrome OS"/>

        <updated>2020-07-06T07:13:16-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/5/system76-unleash_your_robot_blue-by_kate_hazen_of_system76-e4dcb9252f.png" alt="System76 Pop!_OS Desktop Image" />
                    When my son started at his new school, he needed a conventional&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/5/system76-unleash_your_robot_blue-by_kate_hazen_of_system76-e4dcb9252f.png" alt="System76 Pop!_OS Desktop Image" />
                <p>When my son started at his new school, he needed a conventional PC. After finding him a 2015 MacBook Air in perfect condition for a veritable steal on eBay, I adopted his Chromebook – a Dell Inspiron 3180 with an 11.6 inch screen, Intel Celeron processor, 4 GB of RAM and 64 GB of eMMC storage.</p>
<p>I enjoy using it. It runs for 8 or 9 hours on a charge, it has a beautiful HD-ish touch screen and it allows me to install Android apps. These Android apps are treated just like apps on a smartphone, allowing me to access my corporate email and connect to Skype for Business.</p>
<p>I recently used it on a trip to New York City and it fit well on the tray table in United Economy class and was speedy on the in-flight Wi-Fi.</p>
<p>For context, I’ve been using Mac OS X exclusively since OS X Jaguar was released in 2002. I had the privilege of either working for myself or bringing my own device to work, so Mac OS was my daily driver and I became proficient in using it and the software designed for it. That changed in January 2018 when I began working for a large company that standardized on Windows 10 PC’s.</p>
<p>While I still have my 2015 MacBook Pro, my interest in the Chromebook was more about daily, personal use – email, social media, writing, watching videos, doing research – and less about the things I used to do on my Mac which included more advanced workflows like image editing and audio and video production.</p>
<p>After a couple of months, I found the screen on the Chromebook just a wee bit too small and the processor just a wee bit too slow to render web pages and web apps like Office 365 Online (needed for my work), so I started exploring modern Linux distributions.</p>
<h2>Like coming home – only more modern</h2>
<p>Linux is not new to me. I started running Linux under <a href="http://www.slackware.com/announce/1.0.php" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)">Slackware 1.0</a> and had to build a custom PC just to use it, since so few components were supported in the early 90’s. A lot has changed since then.</p>
<p>I decided to experiment with Linux on a more powerful <a href="https://amzn.to/2LvmZ4y" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)">2-in-1 Dell Inspiron 7000</a> device. It’s a great design with a beautiful high resolution Gorilla Glass screen, aluminium body, i7 processor, 16 GB RAM and a lot more storage.</p>
<p>My first few attempts at installation (<a href="https://www.linuxmint.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)">Linux Mint</a>) were challenging. This PC is designed to run Windows 10 and there were some BIOS configuration changes I had to figure out in order to convince the machine that it could install Linux instead of Windows.</p>
<p>After a lot of Googling and even more trial and error, I finally got Linux Mint installed. It’s a vastly better experience than Windows and much more powerful than an off-the-shelf Chromebook. When it comes down to it, I use it for the same tasks as the Chromebook, except I’m not limited to Chrome OS and browser apps – I can run software applications natively in the OS.</p>
<p>I don’t see myself giving up my Mac for a Linux machine for tasks like video editing, podcasting or image editing, but I don’t do those things very often any more. But, with a Linux installation, I have the option to occasionally perform those tasks whereas those options were limited in Chrome OS.</p>
<p>After a few weeks, I felt that Linux Mint was <em>too much</em> like Windows and just didn’t feel like the Chromebook or Mac OS experiences I prefer, so I started looking at other desktop environments.</p>
<p>After exploring vanilla Ubuntu, Elementary OS and Plasma 5, I finally settled on <a href="https://pop.system76.com/docs/difference-between-pop-ubuntu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)">Pop!_OS from System76</a>.</p>
<p>The experience is wonderful – it’s well designed, roomy and feels much more like the elegant experience I’m used to on the Mac. The GNOME-based desktop environment is simple and uncluttered and the speed at which apps perform and web pages load is even faster than my MacBook Pro. (I guess that’s obvious given that the Mac has specs from 2015, but still.)</p>
<p>System maintenance is even more like a Mac. For instance, like Mac OS and Windows 10, the OS lets me know when there are software updates available and prompts me to upgrade. All I have to do is enter my credentials and the OS takes care of everything for me. In the “good old days” of using Linux, I had to monitor the web and Usenet for software updates, then download and compile them from source code.</p>
<p>Those days are gone.</p>
<p>There’s also an “app store” called Pop!_Shop where you can find a curated catalog of commonly used Linux software. Again, all updates are managed by the OS, just like Mac OS or Windows 10.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/5/ezgif.com-video-to-gif.gif" alt="" width="600" height="338">
<figcaption >Pop! Shop</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2>Why not just get a new Mac or a faster Chromebook?</h2>
<p>A new Mac is overkill for my personal computing needs. I love my MacBook Pro and would be happy to be able to use it as my daily driver again, but I don’t see that happening any time soon.</p>
<p>A faster Chromebook would serve my usual needs, but why spend just about as much on a high-performance Chromebook to only have the limited functionality of Chrome OS? (Comparison: <a href="https://amzn.to/38dSQR2" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)">Google PixelBook</a> vs. <a href="https://amzn.to/2s3JTJt" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)">Dell Inspiron 7000</a>)</p>
<p>A Linux laptop running Pop!_OS fits squarely in between an under-powered, education-oriented Chromebook and a new MacBook at a much more competitive price. I get high-performance access to my cloud services but can also occasionally run <a href="https://www.gimp.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)">Gimp</a> for image editing or <a href="https://www.openshot.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)">OpenShot</a> for a quick video edit.</p>
<p>My biggest complaint has been battery life. Again, the battery performance claims for this machine are based on Windows 10 with drivers designed specifically for this hardware. It took me a bit of Googling to learn about modern Linux battery management before I could get the machine to run longer than a couple of hours on a charge. In addition to the Pop!_OS battery management tools (which are pretty good), I eventually installed <a href="https://www.tecmint.com/tlp-increase-and-optimize-linux-battery-life/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)">TLP</a> and <a href="https://www.linuxuprising.com/2018/09/tlpui-is-graphical-user-interface-for.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)">TLPGUI</a> for more advanced battery management. After a few weeks of use with this setup, I’ve found battery life to be more than acceptable.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image" ><img loading="lazy" src="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/5/tlpgui.png" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" srcset="https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/5/responsive/tlpgui-xs.png 300w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/5/responsive/tlpgui-sm.png 480w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/5/responsive/tlpgui-md.png 768w ,https://gadgetboy.org/media/posts/5/responsive/tlpgui-lg.png 1024w"  alt="" width="1024" height="772">
<figcaption >TLP GUI</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2>Is this setup right for you?</h2>
<p>If you’re like me and most of your personal computing is cloud-based (or could be), I think you’d be surprised how much of your needs can be met by a set up like this.</p>
<p>Sure, you might not want to go through the hassle of tweaking the BIOS settings to get Linux to install, but really, once that’s done, installation is just like Mac OS or Windows 10. (<a href="https://system76.com/laptops" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)">You could also buy a machine preloaded with Pop!_OS from System76</a> but that option is not as attractive – both in cost and design – as a PC from a major OEM.)</p>
<p>If you prefer Mac OS-style computing, you can install a desktop environment that looks and behaves almost exactly like the Mac. Ditto for Windows. You can run your favorite browser (<a href="https://itsfoss.com/microsoft-edge-linux/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)">even if your favorite browser is Microsoft Edge</a>) to work with G Suite, Office 365 Online – even Apple iCloud.</p>
<p>That’s because <strong>using</strong> Pop!_OS is easy. If I set up a PC for my wife running Pop!_OS, she could complete her usual tasks with almost no learning curve. But she’s definitely not the sort of person to figure out how to get the PC to accept the installation. It’s not her thing.</p>
<p>Maybe there’s a cottage industry in setting up user-friendly Linux installations on a device that a customer already owns? Probably not enough mass appeal there, but it’s an interesting idea.</p>
<p>If you want a quick run through of Pop!_OS you can watch the short video below. There are plenty of others on YouTube but they’re mostly reviews by Linux geeks, for Linux geeks.</p>
<figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="560" height="314" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/M4TAm9PGvbw" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
